<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The tabernacle of God with men, or, The visible church reformed a discourse of the matter and discipline of the visible church, tending to reformation / by Richard Resbury ...</title>
            <author>Resbury, Richard, 1607-1674.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 184 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 41 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A57068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing R1136A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R32282</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12619249</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12619249</idno>
            <idno type="VID">64467</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A57068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 64467)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1534:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The tabernacle of God with men, or, The visible church reformed a discourse of the matter and discipline of the visible church, tending to reformation / by Richard Resbury ...</title>
                  <author>Resbury, Richard, 1607-1674.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church polity.</term>
               <term>Church discipline.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:64467:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64467:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE Tabernacle <hi>OF</hi> GOD with MEN: OR, <hi>The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſible Church Reformed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Diſcourſe of the Matter and Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline of the Viſible Church, tending to REFORMATION.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Richard Resbury,</hi> Miniſter of the Word in <hi>Oundle,</hi> in <hi>Northamptonſhire.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed in the yeare 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:64467:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:64467:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are many intereſts in this active age contended for; the Soveraign intereſt, the Kings Prerogative, the State inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, the Priviledges of Parliament, the popular intereſt, the Subjects Liberty; there is one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all theſe to be heeded; the intereſt of the Church as more excellent; thoſe civil, this ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritual; thoſe the intereſts of men as men in their ſeverall ſtations, this the intereſt of the Saints as Saints; thoſe making for a politicall, this for a ſpirituall; thoſe for a momentany, this for eternall happineſſe; this the intereſt of Chriſt himſelfe, who is head of his Church aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>well according to her viſible and miniſteriall, as her inviſible and ſaving ſtate; and therfore he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone it is, who appoints her officers, adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, lawes, priviledges, liberties in the grand charter of his word; none of w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi>, may the higheſt upon earth, without <hi>crimen laeſae Majeſtatis,</hi> at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt againſt the Crown of Chriſt, to violate;
<pb facs="tcp:64467:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>Neither is this onely excellent above the reſt, but moſt advantageous to them; It is not onely the piety, but the true policy, of Kings, Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aments and people, to give due heed to the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of this, which ſetled truly, ſettles all theirs ſurely and beautifully. <hi>Be wiſe now therefore O ye Kings, be inſtructed yee Judges of the earth: Kiſſe the Son.</hi> Nay the obtaining of the kingdome of Chriſt in the world in all its claims, ſhall renew the face of the whole Creation, and make a new heaven and a new earth.</p>
            <p>It hath been my endeavour in the integrity of my heart (ſo far as I have obtained mercy to diſcern that deceitful piece) to enquire into the true ſtate and order of the viſible Church of Chriſt; and if I may, to bring ſomething, if but a little Goats haire towards the ſetting up of the Sanctuary; One thing I have labour'd, I hope not unuſeful, to bring down the enquiry particularly to our condition in this Nation, that we might diſtinctly conſider what after ſo many engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to the Lord, by his great works for us, by our ſolemn <hi>Covenant</hi> with him, lies upon us to practiſe. No more; Only I have, if thou beeſt faithfull, thy prayers; if ingenuous, thine indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence, where thou ſhalt finde ſlips.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Thine in the ſervice of the Goſpel,</hi>
RIC. RESBURY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="propositions">
            <pb facs="tcp:64467:3"/>
            <head>The Heads of this enſuing Diſcourſe are theſe eight Propoſitions or Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions following.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>I.</hi> THe true matter of the viſible Church is vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Saints onely.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Diſcipline is an Ordinance of Chriſt, for ordering the viſible Church in her ſeveral Congregations.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>III.</hi> To the people of the Church it belongs by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine right to chuſe their officers.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Chriſt hath committed the power of Diſcipline not to the Officers alone, but to the Church, that is, to the Officers with the brotherhood.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>V.</hi> There is a Church-power formally diſtinct from the Civil.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> That Biſhops in office above Presbyters, are no Church officers of divine inſtitution, it is plead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>Jerome</hi> from Scripture and the higheſt Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel-antiquity.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> To a particular Congregation of viſible Saints,
<pb facs="tcp:64467:4"/>furniſhed with Officers, it belongs to exerciſe all parts of Diſcipline within it ſelfe.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> To a Congregation of viſible Saints, not yet poſſeſt of Officers, it belongs to poſſeſſe themſelves of them.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:64467:4"/>
            <head>The Tabernacle of God with Men. OR, The Viſible Church Reformed.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I. The firſt Inſtruction. <hi>The true Matter of the Viſible Church, is viſible Saints onely.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y viſible Saints we underſtand with <hi>Bucer,</hi> thoſe in whoſe converſation the neceſſary Signes of rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration appear. For clearing this;</p>
               <p n="1">1. We do not mean that the regeneration of the Perſon can be certainly concluded from ſuch a converſation as we here require, becauſe the heart within may not be anſwerable; therefore an hypocrite not diſcerned, may be the true matter of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. But our meaning is, that the converſation muſt be ſuch, as if the heart be anſwerable, it is certaine the Perſon is regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate. To cleare this further by inſtance. Not only ſuch as are commonly granted ſcandalous, are here ſhut out, in whoſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation as ſin reignes, ſo in their heart; for ought that may appeare at the leaſt; but ſuch alſo as we commonly call meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly civill honeſt men, becauſe though their hearts be anſwerable to their converſation, yer are they ſtrangers to regeneration; the Propoſition thus cleared, we come to Arguments to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:64467:5"/>
1. To be viſibly of the Church, is to be viſibly <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed; to be viſibly <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed, is to be viſibly of his faith, and to be viſibly Chriſt's; <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29. <hi>Abrahams</hi> fleſh was to the Jewes the viſible bond of the Covenant; but to the Proſelytes, and to the Gentile Churches not his fleſh, but his faith.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To be viſibly of the Church, is to be ſuch in the ſight of men as they are in the ſight of God, who ſhall indeed be ſaved; and therefore viſibly beleevers, and holy, the people of all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, of all the Priviledges of the Goſpel, therefore a juſtified, a ſanctified people, a people adopted, a people of Communion with God and Chriſt, a people of new obedience, a ſpirituall people, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To be the viſible Church of God, is to be viſibly his Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, viſibly an habitation for himſelfe by his ſpirit; <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.21, 22. but ſuch are only they who are viſibly regenerate. The Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was built of old of poliſht ſtones and coſtly timber, it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived only the clean; the viſible Church now is his viſible Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, made up of lively ſtones into a ſpirituall houſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.5. to abide apart from the unclean, that the preſence of God may fill this Temple of his, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16, 17.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the end of the viſible Church; which is, that God might have an holy people, ſeparate from the world, enjoying all Ordinances performing in ſeverall Congregations all ſolemn worſhip to him, glorifying his name by the light of good works, &amp;c. but only ſuch as are viſibly regenerate, are in any meaſure fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for theſe ends; wicked men quite contrarily affected; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as he is in no wiſe to be owned for a Miniſter of the Church, who is no way fitted for the ends of the miniſtery, but is manifeſtly contrary thereto; ſo neither are they to be owned for members of the Church, who are qualified contrary to the ends of Church-Communion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From Scripture-patterne; who were they that were re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by the Baptiſt and by the Apoſtles? Such as being wrought upon by the word preacht, to an holy Profeſſion, forſaking falſe religions, confeſſing their ſins, profeſſing their faith and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, deſired to be ſolemnly received, and that when the Profeſſion of Chriſtian Religion expoſed to great temptations in the world.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Baptiſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3.6. it is a mean conceit at the beſt,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:64467:5"/>to think ſuch a Confeſſion then ſerved the turne, as was palpably a Prophanation of the name of God, as giving no apparant hopes of repentance; let us hear the judgement of ſome, the moſt approved and excellent Expoſitors. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place thus. This Confeſſion was a Teſtimony of repentance; — that men may rightly offer themſelves to baptiſme, the Confeſſion of ſins is required of them; otherwiſe the whole action was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe but an idle toying; furthermore it is to be obſerved that who are here ſpoken of, were perſons come to years, who we know are not to be admitted promiſcuouſly of the Church, nor by baptiſme to be entred into the body of Chriſt, till they have firſt been tryed. The ſame <hi>Calvin</hi> upon <hi>Acts</hi> 19.18. having witneſſed of thoſe there ſpoken of, that they did indeed teſtify that they were throughly affected with the ſerious fear of God, who did of their own accord confeſſe the crimes of their former life, leaſt by their diſſembling they ſhould inwardly nouriſh the wrath of God; he addes concerning thoſe who came to <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſme, that by the Confeſſion of their ſins, they made pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion that they were not feignedly entred into repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beza</hi> upon the ſame place, <hi>viz. Matth.</hi> 3.6. thus, They are ſaid by the Jewes to confeſſe their ſinnes, who acknowledge themſelves all manner of wayes to be ſinners, and ſeek for par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don from the mercy of God, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.3. &amp;c. Hence it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peares (ſaith he) that <hi>John</hi> admitted none to his Baptiſme but ſuch as gave teſtimony that they ſeriouſly embraced the doctrine of the free remiſſion of ſinnes; and ſuch a like publique confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion was required of the Catechumens in the ancient Church, cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the name of <hi>Exomologeſis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſcator</hi> in his obſervations upon <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 8, 10. ſpeaks thus, Baptiſme is not to be applyed to any of yeares, till he have firſt made confeſſion of his ſinnes, and of his faith in Chriſt, and further promiſe of an holy life: all theſe did <hi>John</hi> require (ſaith he) of thoſe that came to be baptized of him; for the firſt, it is cleare, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. for the ſecond, it is manifeſt out of the words of <hi>Paul, Acts</hi> 19.4. where he ſaith <hi>John</hi> baptized with the baptiſme of repentance, ſaying to the people, that they ſhould beleeve up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him who was to come after <hi>John</hi> himſelfe, that is, Chriſt Jeſus. (Compare <hi>Acts</hi> 8.16.) For the third, it is evident from
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:64467:6"/>
                  <hi>verſe</hi> 8.10. of this third of <hi>Matth</hi> which is particularly declared and applyed to divers kinds of life, <hi>Luke</hi> 3.10. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Thus we ſee theſe excellent men, judicious and ſincere in their generation, gather'd no ſuch ſhuffing concluſions from the hiſtory of <hi>Johns</hi> baptiſm recorded in Scripture, as many of ours are wont to gather, who plead the numbers recorded by <hi>John,</hi> as an argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that he did, and we may receive into Church ſociety all comers: for further diſcovery here, let us look into another Scripture, concerning <hi>John</hi> and thoſe received by him, together with the judgements of thoſe excellent and true hearted Divines upon the place; the text of Scripture is <hi>Matth.</hi> 11.12. and it ſhewes how they were affected at leaſt apparently who came in ſo great numbers to be baptized of <hi>John;</hi> compare it with <hi>Luke</hi> 16.16.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Piſcator</hi> here, It ſhewes the effect of <hi>Johns</hi> Doctrine, to wit, that many embraced that Doctrine with great zeale, and ſo took the Kingdome of heaven as it were by force.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beza. The Kingdome of heaven ſuffereth violence.</hi> They break into it as it were by a certaine force: for this treaſure of our heavenly father lies open (as it were) to all, earneſtly by eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one to be laid hold upon, which he might ſeeme formerly to have hid, as it is unfolded <hi>Rom.</hi> 16.25, 26. which compared with this text now in hand, we are given to underſtand, both how entrance into the Kingdome of heaven is offered us, to wit, by the preaching of the Goſpel, and how offerd it is received by us: truly by force made upon our ſelves for beleeving, and by the perſevering heat of zeal.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Take it by force. Beza</hi> againe, <hi>They ſnatch it to themſelves,</hi> or <hi>they ſtorme it:</hi> a Metaphor taken from Tents, or from ſome Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, which is ſtormed by enemies breaking into it. So that fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent force of the ſpirit is ſignified, by which the faithfull being tranſported, are carried with earneſt deſire and endeavour unto eternal life.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cabvin.</hi> 1. There is no doubt but Chriſt commends the majeſty of the Goſpel upon this ground, that it was ſought after with the ſervent deſire and endeavour of many; for as God had raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up <hi>John</hi> to be the Horald of the kingdome of his Son, ſo he put the efficacy of the ſpirit into his Doctrine, that it ſhould pierce into the hearts of men, and ſhould kindle that their heat:
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:64467:6"/>he addes, from theſe words of Chriſt, we learne what is the true nature and manner of faith, verily that men do not coldly and overly agree to God when he ſpeakes to them, but that with an ardent affection they aſpire after him, and do as it were by a vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>olent endeavour break through.</p>
               <p>Bucer. <hi>The violent take it by force;</hi> that is, they who are ſo enflamed with deſire of the kingdome, that they caſt life and all things behinde their backs, ſo they may be made partakers of the Goſpel, and citizens of the kingdome of heaven; then he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers this place to <hi>Luke</hi> 7.28, 29. &amp; ads, this people, and theſe Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licans, who neglecting all things, received with greateſt zeale the word of God firſt by <hi>John,</hi> then by Chriſt and his diſciples, juſtifying God, that is, as well by free confeſſion of their ſins, as with moſt earneſt, nor leſſe acceptable embracing of offered grace, both acknowledging and proclaiming God juſt, and the ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifier are thoſe violent ones which make force upon the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heaven, and by force take it; and doth not a man ſeem to take that by force, for which he runs the hazard of life? by theſe we are taught, that the treaſure of the Goſpel befals not any but thoſe who have ſought it with moſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deſire, and even love to hazard and loſe al things for it. Thus <hi>Bucer;</hi> hence we ſee how in the judgement of theſe worthy lights in the Church, <hi>Johns</hi> hearers were affected when by him received.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Apoſtles, and thoſe received by them. <hi>Acts</hi> 2.41. to the end, <hi>Acts</hi> 4.32, 33, 34, 35. <hi>Acts</hi> 8.36, 37. read the places; ſee <hi>Calvin</hi> likewiſe upon <hi>Acts</hi> 5.13, where he thus ſhewes of how pure a conſtitution the viſible Church then was; having obſerved it one fruit of the Miracle that unbelie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers affrighted with ſo remarkable a judgement upon <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira,</hi> durſt not contemne the Apoſtles, &amp;c. He addes, though <hi>Luke</hi> aſcribes not this onely to the Miracles, but rather comprehends all things together which might make for the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſing the dignity of the Church; for ſo were all things order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, as that a certaine divine majeſty ſhined among them; for they differed no otherwiſe from others, then Angels do from men; for there is in holy diſcipline, and the ſincere obſervation of godlineſſe, a ſecret kinde of majeſty which awes even the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked whether they will or not; but we are at this day ſtrangers to it; nay, by our prophane libertie of living wickedly, we
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:64467:7"/>render our ſelves together with the Goſpel contemptible. Thus much for the fifth Argument.</p>
               <p n="6">6. From expreſſe Command of the Churches ſeparation from the openly wicked, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17. with the former verſes. <hi>Object.</hi> The wicked here are heathen and profeſt Infidels. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The Apoſtle urgeth in his expoſtulation, <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15, 16. ſuch a repugnancy in the Churches Communion with thoſe wicked ones, as betwixt light and darkneſſe, righteouſneſſe and unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe, Chriſt and <hi>Belial;</hi> that the Church then may anſwer that part of the compariſon which belongs to her, (be thoſe wicked ones who they will,) ſhe muſt conſiſt of a righteous people. 2. If the Church muſt ſeparate from them, becauſe darkneſſe, unrighteouſneſſe, &amp;c. then from thoſe who are ſuch in life, whatſoever in word they profeſſe, being as evill in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture account, as ſuch heathen and termed infidels or unbelee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.15, 16. worſe then profeſt Infidels, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.8. and thoſe who have a forme of Godlines, (and therefore in word profeſſe the true God at the leaſt.) but deny the power of it; guilty of open wickedneſſe, are to be turned from, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.5. 3. Otherwiſe manifeſt Prophanation of the name of God with a palpable lye, 1 <hi>John</hi> 1.6, 7. ſhould entitle to the great honour of Church-Communion, &amp; the great Priviledges thereto belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and the viſible Church ſhould be no Temple refuſing the unclean, but a common Inne for all Commers, a Cage of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clean birds, a Sty for ſwine. 4. Many moſt abominable here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks may in word profeſſe the true God, to whom yet it is granted generally that Church-Communion is to be denied. Adde, <hi>Iſhmael, Eſau, &amp;c.</hi> profeſt the true God, yet they were not of the Church.</p>
               <p n="7">7. From the doctrine of diſcipline; <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15. &amp;c 1. The viſible Church is a brotherhood. <hi>If thy brother ſinne,</hi> &amp;c. and this brotherhood founded in Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 20.17. but doth Chriſt owne as brethren, God as children, any but ſuch as are in ſome degree ſanctified? apparantly ſo, that they may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parantly owned. 2. The duties by our Saviour required in the exerciſe of diſcipline, from any Church member indefinitely, cannot be expected from any other, both here admoniſhing in the three degrees with aime at gaining a brother, &amp;c. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.2. It is required of the Church that they be mourners when
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:64467:7"/>any proves ſcandalous among them; to the Church of which the people are a maine part, is the power of Chriſt committed, for caſting out and delivering up to Satan, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. in caſe of neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect hereof the whole lump is leavened, <hi>viz.</hi> the whole Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is under guilt; neglect here is a ſin tending to the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churching of Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14.20. &amp;c. with all ſcandalous of the Church, familiar ſociety is to be refuſed by every Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, <hi>v.</hi> 9.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch ſeverity herein is required as cannot be exerciſed towards all ſcandalous, with whom we muſt needs have commerce in this world, <hi>v.</hi> 11. the ſcandalous within the Church, when any prove ſuch, are by the Church to be judged; <hi>v.</hi> 12. and put away, <hi>v.</hi> 13. the end of all is to humble, ſhame, and recover the fallen ſinner. Now how can theſe things be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected from the Church, if wicked Perſons ſhall be allowed the matter of the Church? Can they deliver to Satan that are them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves delivered to him? &amp;c. have they ſhare in the power of Chriſt, who are themſelves under the power of Satan? what is there in a company of wicked Perſons, to humble and ſhame a wicked Perſon? how ſhall they act in any of their duties de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon diſcipline, who have no Principles for it? 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. If he that walks inordinately, having been formerly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, muſt be withdrawne from, then ſuch a one not yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, is not to be received; and generally, foraſmuch as ſcandalous when in, are to be caſt out; not in, they are to be left out.</p>
               <p>They who confine all Church-power to the officers alone, will here take offence; that in following this Argument, we al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low a ſhare of that power to the people; to that we ſhall ſpeak more fully and purpoſely hereafter in due place.</p>
               <p n="8">8. From the Teſtimonies given to the Churches in moſt of the Epiſtles, eſpecially about the beginning, as <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.8, &amp; <hi>c.</hi> 15. <hi>v.</hi> 14. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.4. to 10. <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.3. to 9. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.2. to the end. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.3. to 8. read the places; ſo of thoſe ſeven Aſian Churches, ſome very pure, as <hi>Smyrna</hi> and <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> ſo as no fault found with them; others, as <hi>Epheſus, Pergamus</hi> and <hi>Thya<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tira,</hi> a very faire Teſtimony of them, both what they had beene, and what in part they were, though not a little lapſed, but both againſt them, and the other two moſt corrupt, <hi>Sardis</hi> and <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odicea,</hi> their diſchurching is ſeverely threatned, except they ſhall
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:64467:8"/>returne to a purer ſtate. <hi>Object.</hi> The Apoſtle gives a faire Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to the Church of <hi>Corinth,</hi> yet were there many great enormities among them. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. His Teſtimony is to the Church generally, but with exception of ſuch as walke diſorder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the Church, as appears in that. 2. He requires the Church to proceed in way of diſcipline againſt ſuch, ſo as in caſe they perſevere in their evill Courſe, to cut them off from the Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion of Saints; whence 3. it appears that in their admiſſion they were not diſcovered ſuch; whence that which may hence be gathered is, that a Church rightly conſtitute, is not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently upon her degenerating in many of her members to be forſaken, but they ſo degenerating to be cut off 4. The retai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of ſuch in the Church, involved the whole Church in guilt and threatned wrath, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.6. and <hi>c.</hi> 11.30. ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.14, 15, 16, 20. &amp;c. whence we may lay down this Concluſion, ſuch perſons are not the true matter of the Church, the retaining of whom in the Church makes evidently for her deſtruction; but ſuch are the openly wicked &amp; foul hereticks 5. However the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> was by her falſe Teachers firſt ſtaggered out of the way in ſomething of doctrine, and thence grew remiſſe in diſcipline for a time; yet it appears by their ſpeedy and ſound repentance, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. that they were generally and habitually a very holy people.</p>
               <p n="9">9. From the practiſe of the primitive Churches after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times, in two things it appears how choice the matter of the Church then was.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all of their Catechumens, when any formerly hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, wrought upon by the preaching of the Goſpel, profeſſed their embracing of the Chriſtian Religion, renouncing their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer folſe worſhip, and deſired the Church to take them into her care for their ſpirituall ſtate; the Church accordingly took them into her care for inſtruction and edifying, but did not receive them into her fellowſhip, any further then to heare the word, till they gave a good account both of their Chriſtian knowledge and Chriſtian converſation, and that in time of greateſt Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; and all the time that they ſtood thus upon tryal, and under inſtruction rending to prepare them for admiſſion, they were called <hi>Catechumens;</hi> when after a certaine time of tryall they moved to be admitted into Church fellowſhip, they were called
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:64467:8"/>Competents or deſirers; when they were admitted, it was by baptiſme, and then were they compleat members of the Church, and called the faithfull; This was one ſort of <hi>Catechumens;</hi> Another ſort there was; the children of Chriſtian Parents, who having been in their infancy baptized, yet when they were grown to years, they were under the Churches inſtruction and tryall, juſt in the ſame manner as the former, and held the place and name of <hi>Catechumens,</hi> till they were for knowledge and holineſſe of converſation approved experimentally by the Church; then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their deſires they were received into Church-fellowſhip by ſolemne impoſition of hands, and ſo admitted to the Lords Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, and brought under diſcipline, and were now compleat mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers of the Church; this impoſition of hands being grounded up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.2. whence by the corruption of Popery, it degene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated into that ſpurious Ordinance of confirmation as they cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led it.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Their ſeverity towards the lapſed; it is well knowne to all acquainted with the manner of the Church in thoſe times, that as they diligently caſt out the ſcandalous, ſo they ſtood up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtrict termes with them, before they would upon their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of repentance receive them againe; this, together with the ſtate of thoſe times conſidered, times of great perſecution, it may be gathered, that they received only ſuch into Church-fellowſhip, as whom they might conceive ſo principled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as to prefer the truth and purity of Goſpel Profeſſion to their own lives. Let us here ſprinkle ſome few Teſtimonies found in the Fathers of thoſe times, touching the purity of the Church in the matter of it. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apologetick, <hi>c.</hi> 2. alledgeth <hi>Pli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> an heathen, Deputy-Governour under <hi>Trajan</hi> an heathen Emperour, about a hundred years after Chriſt, giving this Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony to the Chriſtians generally, <hi>That beſides their ſtiffe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſall to ſacrifice, he found nothing in their religious worſhip, but that they had meetings before day to ſing to Chriſt and to God, and by mutuall agreement to conſtrme diſcipline, and that they forbad murder, adultery fraud, treachery, and other wickedneſſes:</hi> The ſame Father who himſelfe lived a little more then two hundred years after Chriſt, he is much in challenging the perſecuting powers, to make good any of thoſe crimes which they charged upon Chriſtians, as <hi>atheiſme, inceſt, infant-murder, treaſon,</hi> char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:64467:9"/>them that they warre with the name of Chriſtians; that an innocent name in innocent men is by them hated and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuted.</p>
               <p>In the 39 <hi>ohapt.</hi> of his <hi>Apologetick,</hi> thus, We are a body made up of the conſcience of Religion, of the unity of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline, of the Covenant of hope; then ſpeaking of their worſhip in the publique Aſſembly, he addes for diſcipline; there like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe are Exhortations, Caſtigations, and Divine Cenſures; for with great weight is judgement paſt, as among thoſe that are certaine that the eye of God is upon them, and it is the greateſt fore-judgement of the judgement to come, if any one ſhall ſo offend as that he is caſt out from the communication of prayer, of aſſembling, and of all holy commerce. He mentions in the ſame chapter the love of the Chriſtians to be ſuch one towards another, that the Heathen were wont with indignation to ſay of them, <hi>Behold how they love one another, and are ready to die one for another.</hi> In the 46. <hi>chapt.</hi> of his <hi>Apologetick</hi> he ſhewes how they bore not with any of evill converſation, comparing the Chriſtians with the Philoſophers. The Philoſophers, ſaith he, have an apiſh affectation of the truth, and by their affectation cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt it, as hunting after their owne praiſe. The Chriſtians ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily deſire it, and performe it intirely, as providing for their owne ſalvation; He adds a little after this objection; But ſome of ours depart from the rule of diſcipline; to which he anſwers; they are no longer owned for Chriſtians by us; and he reproves it in the Philoſophers, that ſuch among them as walk not accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rules of Philoſophy are yet called by the name, and have ſtill the honour of Philoſophers. In his Book to <hi>Scapula,</hi> who was a Deputy-Governour under the Romane Emperour, and a perſecutor, he gives this character of the Chriſtians, beſides their unſhaken piety towards God, refuſing the Heathen ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices againſt the greateſt torments, We defraud none, we adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terate the mariage of none, we handle Orphans religiouſly, we relieve the needy, to none do we render evill for evill; let them who bely our profeſſion look to it: (that is, they who in word profeſſe themſelves Chriſtians, but walk not accordingly) whom we our ſelves refuſe. Who is there that complaines of us upon any other ground but onely that we are Chriſtians? for ſo great innocency, for ſo great honeſty, for righteouſneſſe, for chaſtity,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:64467:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>for faith, for truth; for the living God are we burned.</p>
               <p>In his Book of Repentance, <hi>chapt.</hi> 6. ſpeaking of the neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of ſound repentance, and that on the <hi>Catechumens</hi> part, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore baptiſme; <hi>I deny not,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the divine benefit;</hi> that is, <hi>remiſſion of ſinnes to be altogether ſafe to thoſe that ſhall go into the water;</hi> that is, <hi>that ſhall be baptized; but that thou mayeſt come to that, thou muſt be diligent; for who will afford thee, a man of ſuch faithleſſe repentance, one drop of any water?</hi> A little after, <hi>let no man flatter himſelf, that his ranck is yet but among the Catechumens, as though he might therefore take liberty to ſin; as ſoone as thou haſt known the Lord, fear him; as ſoone as thou haſt beheld him, receive him;—is Chriſt one to the baptized, another to the hearers, or Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumens? That Laver is the ſealing up of faith which faith is both begun and commended from the faith of repentance; we are not therefore waſhed,</hi> (viz. <hi>baptized</hi>) <hi>that we may ceaſe to ſinne, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe we have ceaſed, becauſe we are already waſhed in heart;</hi> this is the firſt baptiſm of the <hi>Catechumen,</hi> entire fear. In his book of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Preſcriptions againſt the hereticks, <hi>c.</hi> 41 he makes the promiſcuous matter of the Church the property of the hereticks. <hi>I will not omit</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>the deſcription of the hereticks converſation; how frivolous, how earthly, how humane it is, without gravity, without authority, without diſcipline, ſuch as agrees with their faith; firſt of all it is uncertaine who is a</hi> Catechumen, <hi>and who is one of the faithfull, they go together alike; they hear alike; they pray alike; Nay if the heathen ſhould come among them</hi> (in their Aſſemblies) <hi>they would caſt that which is holy to dogs, and Pearls (though no true ones) to the ſwine, their Proſtration of diſcipline they call ſimplicity; our care of it, they call an over-curious trimming, they receive all promiſcuouſly to the Lords Supper, — with them the</hi> Catechumens <hi>go for perfect before they be throughly inſtructed.</hi> He chargeth it upon them, that they are more in labouring for number then due matter. <hi>No where</hi> ſaith he <hi>are more eaſie termes then in the tents of the rebels; where this very thing to be is to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve.</hi> In his Book of Baptiſme, Cap. 18. he thus ſpeaks. <hi>That Baptiſme is not raſhly to be betruſted, let them know whoſe office it is; Give to every one that askes, hath its proper title belonging to Almes. That rather is to be heeded; Give not that which is holy to dogs; and do not caſt your Pearls to ſwine; and lay hands ſudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly on no man, that thou beeſt not Partaker of other mens ſins, &amp;c.</hi>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:64467:10"/>Where (by the way) he interprets impoſition of hands there to point at ſolemne admiſſion of Church-members; Thus for ſome gleanings out of <hi>Tertullian.</hi> The like we might obſerve from others; as in <hi>Cyprian,</hi> who will have the Church to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt of the miniſtery and the ſtanding people; and againſt what temptations did they then ſtand? and for their Communion, they were moſt impatient of hereticks and all ſcandalous. In his 55. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> writing to <hi>Cornelius</hi> then Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> about ſuch as having formerly fallen, were now ſeeking to be againe received into the Church, thus he ſpeaks; <hi>For ſome, their crimes are ſo much againſt them, or the brethren (that is the ſtanding people,) do ſo firmely and ſtiffely reſiſt, that they can by no means be received <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> with the ſcandal and danger of very many;—O if thou couldſt (moſt beloved brother) be here with us, when thoſe evill and perverſe ones returne from their ſchiſme, thou ſhouldſt ſee what a do I have to perſwade our brethren (the People) to Patience, that they would, having allayed their grief of mind, conſent to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving and taking care of the wicked; for as they rejoyce and are glad, when ſuch as are tolerable and leſſe faulty returne, ſo on the other hand they murmure and contend earneſtly when deplored Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and ſtubborne, and ſuch as are defiled with adulteries, or with idols, or ſuch as are proud, come back, &amp;c.</hi> but I will be no fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther tedious in quotations of this nature. If any man deſire any further ſatisfaction, let him read the laſt Section of the ſixt Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter in the three firſt Centuries. <hi>Magdeburg.</hi> Concerning the converſation and diſcipline of Chriſtians, afterwards in <hi>Auſtins</hi> time, when ſome would have it, that the Profeſſion of the Chriſtian faith ſhould entitle to baptiſme, though accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with a wicked life, He writes a book entitled of Faith and Works, proving ſuch a Profeſſion to be as no Profeſſion.</p>
               <p n="10">10. From the ſtate of new <hi>Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21.27. from this and the laſt Argument it is manifeſt, that before the myſtery of iniquity prevailed farre, and after it ſhall ceaſe, the viſible Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches owne no ſcandalous ſinners of their ſociety; the promiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuous ſtate then of the Churches in this degeneration, is the outward Court unmeaſured, and the Holy City trod under foot by the Gentiles. That voice then <hi>Rev.</hi> 18.4. calling the people of God out of <hi>Babylon,</hi> cals for the Churches ſeparation from
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:64467:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſuch; this Confuſion now obtaining, being one ſtraine of Popiſh corruption, with Popery beginning and ending.</p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>Conſectary.</head>
                  <p>From this diſcourſe of the matter of the Church; foraſmuch as experience ſhowes that in all nations where the Goſpell is preached, yet the greateſt part of men are manifeſtly wicked; it cannot be according to rule, that all the people of any nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on generally ſhould be accounted of the Church, though in word they profeſſe the true religion, which they know little of, and care leſſe for; but in every nation, and Congregation or Town, a diſtinction ought to be kept betwixt the Church and the world, and the two ſorts of <hi>Catechumens</hi> ought to be ſome, the children of the Church, and therefore baptized in infancy, upon their due tryall when come to years, received ſolemnely to Church-Communion, as to the Supper, Diſcipline, &amp;c. O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers not the children of the Church, received upon due tryall by baptiſme, when come to years.</p>
                  <p>This concluſion is further made good from the exerciſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9, 10, 11. If all the nation generally be of the Church, then are all the ſcandalous of the nation generally the ſcandalous of the Church; but that they are not; with all that are ſcandalous of the Church, we muſt refuſe familiar ſociety, not ſo much as familiarly eating with them, (ſome peculiar rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions here reſerved) and yet abide in the world; but with all ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous in the nation, we cannot ſo refuſe, except we will go out of the world as the Apoſtle there argues, and experience to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry impartiall and unblaſſed ſpirit abundantly makes it good.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II. <hi>Diſcipline is an Ordinance of Chriſt, for ordering the viſible Church in her ſeverall Congregations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>WE ſhall now briefly, (but yet ſo as to omit none that ſeem to have any weight in them,) endeavour the anſwer of Objections.</p>
               <p n="1">
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:64467:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
1. Such as are generall; as</p>
               <p n="1">1. That there were ſo many wicked among the Jewes, and yet that Church was not to be forſaken;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That miniſtration was more carnall, and therefore a more carnal might then paſſe, <hi>Heb.</hi> 9 10. As the Goſpell mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtration is more ſpirituall, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.10, 11. ſo that the Goſpell people may appear to be the people of that miniſtration, they muſt in appearance be more ſpirituall.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Nor otherwhere for that time could Church-communion be enjoyed, God having confined it to that nation, to that Prieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood, and that Temple; and therefore though their Prieſts and People generally proved as great Idolaters and Perſecutors as the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> this day, yet the faithfull among them muſt there remaine, to offer ſacrifice and worſhip God; but in the times of the Goſpel, where any Church turnes idolatrous and Perſecutors of the truth, there is liberty otherwhere to ſettle Church-Communion purely.</p>
               <p n="3">3. That People were holy in their admiſſion. 1. In <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> family, <hi>Gen.</hi> 18.18, 19. 2. In their nationall planting, <hi>Judg.</hi> 2.6, 7, 10. hence that Teſtimony given of them, that they were planted a noble vine, wholly a right ſeed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 2.21.</p>
               <p n="4">4. It was by rule provided for among them, that none exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally wicked ſhould enjoy Church-Communion; the mixture, that was beſide the rule, and therefore no plea at all. 1. None were circumciſed but ſuch as were externally holy; their in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants by deſcent from <hi>Abraham,</hi> being borne Church-members within the miniſtration of the Covenant, the fleſh of <hi>Abraham</hi> entitling that nation to the Covenant, and there was their claim to circumciſion, that they were that ſeed of <hi>Abraham,</hi> whatever their immediate Parents were; and they in their infancy had done nothing to make void that claime.</p>
               <p>The Proſelites that they might be circumciſed, muſt give evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of <hi>Abrahams</hi> faith, and walk in his ſteps, and then they being <hi>Abrahams</hi> adopted ſeed, their children had the ſame title to circumciſion, as the children of the Jews.</p>
               <p>In the Goſpel Churches there muſt be a viſible deſcent from <hi>Abraham</hi> according to the faith, for right unto baptiſme, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for our ſelves or ſeed, baptiſme being the Seale of that Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant which bleſſeth all the nations of the earth in the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> by faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:64467:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Thus they were holy in their circumciſion. 2. For other pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culiar Ordinances, there was a threefold barre to ſuch as were openly wicked.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Ceremoniall; divers caſes of Ceremoniall uncleannes which debarred Communion in the peculiar Ordinances; and they that were moſt careleſſe of the holy things of God, would ofteneſt be taken in theſe Ceremoniall ſnares.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Judiciall; the ſame Covenant that entitled them to the Church, entitled them likewiſe to that land, whence divers ſorts of wicked perſons were to be cut off from life; not only blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemers, but idolaters; nor only murthers, but adulterers; nor only traitors, but diſobedient to Parents, &amp;c. hence the whole nation enjoyned, (as in <hi>Aſa's</hi> time,) to ſwear a ſolemne Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant for ſeeking the Lord God of their fathers, with all their heart and all their ſoule, and to performe it under penalty of death, whether great or ſmall, whether man or woman, <hi>Chron.</hi> 2.15, 12, 13. Now had the judiciall law been executed accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to divine rule, partly ſo many wicked ones had been coct off; and partly the reſt had been ſo formidably warned, that here had been a great prevention of that mixture in their Church-Communion.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Eccleſiaſtical; <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.26. difference to be made by Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical power, as well betwixt the holy and prophane, (and thoſe are morall termes,) as betwixt the clean and unclean, (which are ceremoniall termes) A generall rule for this, underſtood by the learned of Eccleſiaſticall cutting off <hi>Numb.</hi> 15.30, 31. the ſtranger there the Proſelyte of the Covenant; further Teſtimony to this rule, that the openly wicked were eccleſiaſtically to be cut off, is the ordinance of excommunication among them, in the three degrees of it; <hi>Niddui Cherem,</hi> and <hi>Maran-atha.</hi> A thorow diſcourſe about this, for further ſatisfaction, ſee in <hi>Gillaſpies Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rons Rod bloſſoming.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus much for this Objection, which is wont much to be ſtood upon; but how ſandy a foundation it is, fit for ſo rotten a building, as many endeavour to ſet upon it, I hope by this time appears.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Obiect.</hi> 2. The Parable of the tares, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.24. to the 31. and 37 to the 44 verſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. The field is the world, <hi>v.</hi> 38. the good ſeed are
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:64467:12"/>the children of the Kingdome, the tares are the children of the wicked one. <hi>ibid.</hi> theſe make the viſible Church in the world according to the minde of the parable; both theſe are to grow together untill the harveſt, <hi>v.</hi> 30. what will hence follow? that Perſons apparantly wicked, muſt be received into, and retained in the viſible Church? this puts the parable upon the rack, and forceth it to ſpeak what it intends not. 1. It warrants not the receiving wicked Perſons into the Church. <hi>v.</hi> 25. 1. The hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bandmmen were not ſo watchfull as they ſhould have been, when the enemy ſowed theſe tares; and it is the enemy not the Lord of the field that ſowes them. 2. Nor the retaining them; then ſhould our Saviour here be againſt himſelfe otherwhere, where he hath appointed the Ordinance of Church cenſure for caſting out ſuch, and that under ſo great a penalty, as for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly we have ſeene, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18. 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. <hi>Revel.</hi> 2. &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If then the gathering up theſe tares, deſired by the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>v.</hi> 28. and forbidden by the maſter, <hi>v.</hi> 29. be meant of Eccleſiaſtical caſting out; theſe cares muſt not be the openly wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, but cloſe hypocrites; yet by ſome of the ſervants of more piercing judgements then others diſcerned; the reaſon given may ſeem to favour this, <hi>v.</hi> 29. They were ſuch as were ſo hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcerned from the wheat, that there was danger of rooting up the wheat, if theſe tares ſhould be gathered up; to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe <hi>Jerome</hi> witneſſeth, that in thoſe countryes there are certain tares, ſo like to wheat in their firſt ſpringing, as hardly to be diſcerned from it; thus <hi>Cyprian</hi> underſtands it; taxing the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolency of <hi>Novatian,</hi> who would not receive the lapſed againe into the Church, though they expreſt never ſo much repentance; <hi>How great arrogance is this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he ſhould think he can do that which our Saviour granted not to the Apoſtles, that he ſhould diſcerne the tares from the wheat?—If he will make himſelfe the ſearcher and the judge of the heart and reins, &amp;c.</hi> Cypr. Epiſt. 52. but in caſting out the openly wicked, there is no danger of this.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Some think it not to be meant of Eccleſiaſticall caſting out; and therfore let the tares be granted for the openly wicked, this parable gives them no place in the viſible Church. 1. This ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering up the tares is their rooting up, (for that expreſſion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:64467:12"/>no leſſe, leſt ye root up alſo the wheat with them, <hi>v.</hi> 29.) and therefore the final deſtruction of theſe wicked Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons; but Church cenſure is not for deſtruction, (except of the fleſh) but for ſalvation of the Perſon. 2. This gathering up deſired here by the ſervants and by the maſter for the preſent denied, is that which ſhall be at the end of the world, the finall deſtruction of the wicked, <hi>v.</hi> 40, 41, 42. they ſhall not then for the preſent gather them up, that is, not knowing of what ſpirit they are, call for fire from heaven againſt them. The like interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is made of the drawnet and the ſeparation of the good from the bad, gathered together by it, <hi>v.</hi> 47. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 3. <hi>Judas</hi> received the Supper, at leaſt the Paſſeover which was a Sacrament; and the Sacraments belong only to thoſe of the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. If we ſhall hence conclude that the openly wicked have right to the Sacraments, and ſo are the true matter of the viſible Church. 1. We muſt deny any ſuch Ordinance as diſcipline. 2. By the ſame reaſon we muſt affirme that a miniſter of the Church, openly knowne to be ſuch an one, as hath his heart ſet to overthrow the Goſpel, and betray the Lord for money, is to be retained in the miniſtery, nay, that ſuch an one ſo knowne before-hand is to be choſen into the miniſtery; for all this Chriſt knew of <hi>Judas,</hi> therefore 3. <hi>Judas</hi> his wickedneſſe was knowne to Chriſt as God, but not as man; but for caſting out of the Church, the offence muſt be knowne to the Church, in a Church way, that is by experience and proof.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 4. The Apoſtles received ſuch as offered themſelves ſuddenly, among the reſt <hi>Simon Magus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> But yet upon ſuch evidence, as amounted in the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of rationall charity, to the evidence of regeneration; for this, 1. Conſider upon what ground they offered themſelves, the Word powerfully preached, and mightily by miracles de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared the Word of God. 2. What was the ſtate of thoſe times. 1. They were times wherein according to former Prophecies the ſpirit was plentifully powred out, by the miniſtery of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles. 2. They were times of great Perſecution of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian faith; nothing of outward advantage to move, but all to the contrary; to preach the Goſpel then among the Jewes, was as it would be now to preach the truth among the Papiſts; to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:64467:13"/>preach it then in the other nations, was as it would be now to preach it among the Turks. If upon the powerfull preaching the truth in the maine points of religion, contrary to the maine Popiſhand Turkiſh tenets, whereof they are moſt zealous, ſuch and ſuch in the midſt of the Popiſh and Turkiſh dominions, ſhould againſt manifeſt and great temptations openly embrace and profeſſe the truth, ſuch a Profeſſion would amount to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther kinde of evidence, then is generally pleaded for from thoſe examples among us. 3. God for vindicating his name a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſcandalous Profeſſion, put forth his revenging judgements againſt the deceitfull and hollow, as in <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Saphira's</hi> caſe, whence many were much deterred from joyning with the Church; <hi>Acts</hi> 5.13. thus for the ſtate of thoſe times. Then thirdly conſider what a faire profeſſion <hi>Simon Magus</hi> made, and for ſome time continued in, which argues ſeemingly no ſmall change, <hi>Acts</hi> 8.13. it is ſaid he beleeved, he continued with <hi>Philip;</hi> he was taken with admiration, &amp;c. ſo <hi>Ananias</hi> and <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phira</hi> made a faire Profeſſion to ſell their Poſſeſſion for reliefe of the Church. 4. When <hi>Simon</hi> diſcovers his rottenneſſe, then, not till then, <hi>Peter</hi> perceived the wickedneſſe of his heart, <hi>v.</hi> 23. and when he perceives it, he profeſſeth he hath no lot among them, becauſe his heart is not right, <hi>v.</hi> 21. yet was not <hi>Peter</hi> without hope but he might repent, <hi>v.</hi> 22, and ſomething hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſtill doth <hi>Simon</hi> appeare; <hi>v.</hi> 24. And now the anſwer to this inſtance may cleare all other of the like nature. There is a fifth,</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 5. The ſcandalous mentioned in ſome of the Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, as in the Church of <hi>Corinth;</hi> but this hath been anſwered before in the eighth Argument; and theſe are all the objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons I know that have any colour in them or at the leaſt in the anſwers to theſe, the grounds are laid for anſwering the reſt. We come now</p>
               <p n="2">2. To peculiar Objections, reſpecting the generality of our people in this kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 1. We are all of the Church by baptiſme al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. From the beginning it was not ſo, that all ſhould be ſo promiſcuouſly received; therefore it behoves us to returne to the firſt patterne; what right have they to baptiſme for their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:64467:13"/>ſeed, themſelves having been baptized, who had none for themſelves, were they unbaptized? 2. <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau</hi> were circumciſed, yet afterward unchurched; ſo were the Sheche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites circumciſed; Many Heathens in <hi>America</hi> baptized by the Spaniard, yet none of theſe ever of the Church.</p>
               <p n="3">3. To receive to baptiſme for themſelves or ſeed groſſe igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants, who underſtand not the ground, nature, and end of that Ordinance, is 1. To make the ſervice of God in ſo maine an Ordinance an unreaſonable ſervice. 2. To make up the viſible Church in her ſeveral congregations by an implicit faith. 4. To admit the ſcandalous in like manner for themſelves or ſeed, is not to ſet the Seale to the Covenant, but to paſſe it againſt the Covenant. 5. The Reformed Churches receive not to the Lords Supper and other priviledges of Church-Communion, ſuch as were baptized in their infancy, but upon tryall of their knowledge and Chriſtian converſation; which, when approved, they ſolemnely admit them; underſtanding Impoſition of hands, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. to point at the ſolemne admiſſion of ſuch. So <hi>Calvin</hi> upon the place, pleading thence for infant-baptiſme. <hi>Reply.</hi> But children may have right by former Anceſtors. <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Viſible adminiſtration muſt have viſible grounds; it muſt therefore upon particular evidence appeare to the Church, that ſuch Anceſtors they had; in whoſe name they may have right. 2. How farre may we go back, and where muſt we ſtop? 3. Offer ſuch reaſoning to thy Prince, will it paſſe for currant, if thou ſhouldeſt claime the Armes and Honour of ſome noble family, meerly upon this ſuppoſition, that it may be ſome of thine Anceſtors were poſſeſſed thereof? 4. Such as could not finde their regiſter for the line of the Prieſthood, were as polluted, put from their office, <hi>Ezra</hi> 1.62. 5. This will prevent the diſtinction betwixt the Church and the world, and keep off for ever the baptiſme of growne men. 6. As for the children of wicked Parents circumciſed among the Jewes, this ſtone hath been removed before, they had by <hi>Abraham</hi> viſible right under whom they fell.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> 2. But all ſorts among us have likewiſe received the Supper.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. But the greateſt part beſides the rule, as is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent upon the ſame grounds now pleaded againſt promiſcuous
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:64467:14"/>baptiſme. 2. In the Reformed Churches, when any member of one Congregation tranſplants to another, notwithſtanding he hath received the Supper formerly in the Church whence he came, yet doth the Church to which he is come, examine and approve him for knowledge and converſation, before they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive him to the Supper.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How or by what right have the Sacraments been ordinari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred in diverſe of our Congregations, where the word hath not been ordinarily preached?</p>
               <p>From the doctrine of the matter of the Church, we may lay downe ſome further Practicall Concluſions.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Saints are to ſeparate from the wicked, into Church-Communion. 1. Otherwiſe the Church cannot be made up only of its due matter; God cannot have his Temple. 2. The Command is expreſſe for it; as we have ſeen in the ſixth Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the Saints as expreſſely called to this, as <hi>Abraham</hi> out of <hi>Caldea,</hi> as the people of God out of <hi>Babylon.</hi> 3. To this ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Communion belongs far greater bleſſings, then to belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers in promiſcuous ſtanding, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.17, 18. generally what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever bleſſings belong to the viſible Church, may be clearlyeſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected, and are moſt fully beſtowed upon the Church, when moſt truly and purely ſetled in her Congregations; the preſence of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.1. his Protection and Defence and Comforts, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 4.5. the power of Chriſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.4. When we have ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken to the diſcipline, we ſhall have further evidences of this Concluſion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No Perſon habitually ſcandalous is to be received to the Sacrament, though he humbles himſelfe before the Church, till ſome time of tryall.</p>
               <p>He is not true matter of the Church, who is not habitually in the Churches eye righteous. But the Sacraments are peculiar Church-Ordinances.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> He that hears not the Church, is to be refuſed; but he that hears her, is to be received; now he that humbles himſelf before the Church upon her admonition, hears her.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. That rule If he hear not the Church, is concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a brother, one within, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.12. but no Perſon habitually ſcandalous is a brother, as the doctrine of the matter of the Church hath evinced.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:64467:14"/>
2. For a brother fallen into ſome ſcandalous ſinne, and hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling himſelfe; it follows not, that he is not to be caſt out, therefore he is ſuddenly to be received: he is neither to be ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly caſt out, nor ſuddenly received to the Sacrament, but to ſtand under further tryall; otherwiſe 1. Church-admonitions will be turned into a meer mockery, execution of cenſure a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the moſt impudent for ever prevented, who will quickly in appearance humble themſelves if that may ſerve the turne; ſuch a courſe of diſcipline will in ſtead of humbling, harden, like the Papiſts abſolution, upon their formal auricular confeſſion and indulgences. 2. For him in ſuch a caſe to deſire ſudden re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, is ſcandalous, an evidence that he is not humbled; which if he were, he himſelfe would not venture ſo ſoone upon his own heart.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Matth. 18.21, 22. with Luk. 17.3, 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> It is a Precept againſt revenge; it is Perſonal, not Eccleſiaſtical forgiveneſſe here commanded; forgiveneſſe of the heart, not of the Court; of an injury againſt me, not of a ſinne againſt God, and even betwixt man and man; this forbids not but a man may proſecute the law againſt the treſpaſſer in diverſe caſes, and yet from the heart forgive him and pray for him.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Concluſ.</hi> Hence the vanity of that argument, uſed by ſome who refuſe to joyne apart from the ſcandalous in a true way of Church-Communion and diſcipline; To the pure all things are pure; therefore the wickedneſſe of others defiles not me, receiving the Sacrament with them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thy ſin defiles thee, and it is thy ſin to keep off from the true way of the viſible Church.</p>
               <p>Suppoſe in a ſetled Church, a Perſon juſtly excommunicate; thou ſhouldſt defile thy ſelfe, if thou ſhouldeſt receive with him, becauſe thou violateſt the order of the Goſpel; ſo here.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:64467:15"/>
               <head>CHAP. III. The ſecond Inſtruction. <hi>Diſcipline is an Ordinance of Chriſt, for ordering the viſible Church in her ſeverall Congregations.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAt.</hi> 18.15. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3.6. <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.2, 14, 20. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20. Theſe Scriptures peruſed, ſhew us both that there is a diſcipline, and what it is.</p>
               <p>For the nature and uſe of diſcipline, together with the obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, lying upon Chriſtians in their places for indeavouring it, I ſhall gather ſomething out of Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> that excellent Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine. <hi>Medull. l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 37.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Holy diſcipline is the Perſonall application of the Will of God by cenſures, either for preventing ſcandals, or for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving them out of the Church of God.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the preaching of the Word, the Will of God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded and really applyed for begetting and increaſing of faith and obedience. In the adminiſtration of the Sacraments the Will of God is perſonally applyed by Seals, for confirming faith and obedience. In the exerciſe of diſcipline the Will of God is perſonally applyed by cenſures, for removing of ſins which fight againſt true faith and obedience.</p>
               <p n="3">3. This diſcipline is inſtituted by Chriſt, <hi>Mat.</hi> 16.19. and <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. and is therefore plainely of divine right; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther may it by men at pleaſure be taken away, diminiſhed or changed.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Nay he ſins againſt Chriſt the Author and Ordainer, who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever doth not what in him lies to ſettle and promote this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline in the Churches of God.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The perſons about whom it ought to be exerciſed, are the members of the viſible inſtitute Churches, without any exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.11. and no others, <hi>verſe</hi> 12. To all and onely thoſe it belongs, to whom it belongs to receive the Sacraments. An inſtitute Church is a particular Congregation of viſible beleevers, joyned together by ſpecial bond, expreſſe
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:64467:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>or implicite for exerciſing the communion of Saints conſtantly among themſelves, <hi>cap.</hi> 32.</p>
               <p n="6">6. In thoſe perſons it hath reſpect to ſinnes and ſcandals; for it is an healing medicine for the wounds and diſeaſes to which the ſheep of Chriſt are ſubject, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.5.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Becauſe it doth effectually urge obedience to Chriſt, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore not without ſingular reaſon, a great part of the Kingdome of Chriſt, as he doth viſibly rule his Church, is by the beſt Divines placed in this Diſcipline. Hence likewiſe the Keyes, (and one of them is the Key of Diſcipline) are called the Keyes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome; and the operations of this Key, binding, looſing, open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhutting the Kingdome of heaven, have upon them the ſtamp of Chriſts kingly authority.</p>
               <p n="8">8. And this is the true reaſon why in ſo few Churches, the Diſcipline of Chriſt, together with the Doctrine, is throughly ſetled and exerciſed, becauſe very many of thoſe who will ſeeme to know Chriſt, and to hope in him, do yet refuſe to receive the whole Kingdome of Chriſt, and to give up themſelves altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther unto him.</p>
               <p n="9">9. And as it is part of the Kingdome of Chriſt, ſo by the ſame reaſon, it is part of the Goſpel; for it is an holy manner of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting the Goſpel, appointed in the Goſpel it ſelfe; therefore they do neither receive the whole kingdome of Chriſt, nor the whole Goſpel, who reject Diſcipline.</p>
               <p n="10">10. But becauſe every part of the kingdome of Chriſt is in its place neceſſary, and that part eſpecially which doth effectually repreſſe ſinne; therefore we may not ſafely enough reſt in thoſe Churches which want Diſcipline, except that publique want be made up by private care and mutuall watching.</p>
               <p n="11">11. The parts of this Diſcipline, are two
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Brotherly admonition.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Excommunication.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Which in caſe of repentance approved to the Church, is ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Abſolution.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Brotherly admonition is to be exerciſed in caſe of any ſin, for which Diſcipline is appointed as a medicine, but after a diverſe manner, according to the difference of ſecret and open ſins. In ſecret ſins, thoſe three degrees are to be obſerved which Chriſt preſcribed in order, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17, but in publike
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:64467:16"/>ſins thoſe degrees are not neceſſary, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.20.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Full Excommunication is not to be exerciſed, except ſtub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bornneſſe be added to the ſin, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. for the ſinner duly admoniſhed, muſt needs either appeare penitent or ſtubborne; the penitent is not to be excommunicate, therefore onely the ſtubborn.</p>
               <p n="14">14. When the matter may ſufferdelay, it is agreeable to Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture and reaſon, that Excommunication be begun by ſuſpending from the Lords Supper, and ſuch like priviledges of the Church, which is commonly called the leſſe Excommunication.</p>
               <p n="15">15. But in this degree we muſt not reſt, but repentance is by this meanes, and in this ſpace to be urged, of which if there be no hopes, we muſt then go on to a compleat ſeparation from the communion of the faithful, which is commonly called the greater Excommunication.</p>
               <p n="16">16. But becauſe the ſtubborne ſinner cannot be ſeparated from the faithful, except the faithful alſo be ſeparated from him, and this makes for the wholſome ſhaming of the ſinner, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3.14. therefore they who are juſtly excommunicate, are to be ſhunned by all Communicants; not as to duties ſimply morall or otherwiſe neceſſary, but as to thoſe parts of converſation, which are wont to accompany approbation and inward familiarity.</p>
               <p n="17">17. From the bond of Excommunication no impenitent per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is to be looſed, neither ought Abſolution to be denied to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny penitent; but it is not ſufficient repentance for a man to ſay, I repent me, I will do no more; except he otherwiſe make proof of true repentance; but ſuch tokens of true repentance ought to appeare, that the Church may be bound to reſt in them; other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe hypocriſie is nouriſhed, and both the Church and Chriſt himſelfe are mocked.</p>
               <p>From this diſcourſe of Diſcipline, beſides the nature of it, appears</p>
               <p n="1">1. The weight of it, binding to wrath, or looſing from it, retaining, or remitting ſins, opening the kingdome of heaven to the penitent, or ſhutting it againſt the impenitent, caſting out of the commonion of the faithfull, cutting off from the body of Chriſt, delivering over to Satan or readmiſſion into the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of the faithfull, reimplanting into the body of Chriſt, reſcue from their ſubjection to Satan; and ſo as all this done
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:64467:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>here upon earth, where rightly adminiſtred, is confirmed in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The neceſſity of it; 1. Standing upon ſo cleare a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and inſtitution of Chriſt; therefore being a Goſpel ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, unchangeable: 2. Being ſo maine a part of the viſible kingdome of Chriſt as Mediator. 3. From the ends of it; for reclaiming and gaining of offending brethren; from deterring others from the like offences, for purging out that old leaven which might infect the whole lump, for vindicating the honour of Chriſt, and the holy profeſſion of the Goſpel; and for pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venting the wrath of God which might juſtly fall upon the Church, if they ſhould ſuffer his Covenant and the Seale thereof to be prophaned by notorious and obſtinate offenders.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. The third Inſtruction. <hi>To the people of the Church it belongs by divine right to chuſe their Officers.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THat Chriſt hath appointed Officers in his Church for the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of the Word, Sacraments and Diſcipline, we need not prove; The confirmation of this Propoſition, that the choyce of Officers is the peoples right, makes not a little for the due ſetling the Church. For this, I ſhall do three things, 1. Point to the Scriptures teaching this truth. 2. Adde ſome reaſons accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to Scripture. 3. Give in the teſtimonies, firſt of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, then of the reformed Churches.</p>
               <p n="1">1. For the Scriptures, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.15. <hi>with</hi> 23. The Diſciples go as farre as is poſſible for man to have an hand in chuſing an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who muſt have his commiſſion immediately from God; they appoint two, and give forth lots, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.3, 4, 5. The whole multitude chuſe their Deacons, and preſent them to the Apoſtles for Ordination, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. It is ſaid of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> when they had <hi>ordained</hi> Elders to the Churches; the word tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated <hi>ordained,</hi> ſignifies ſolemnely to appoint to office upon the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:64467:17"/>peoples vote or choyce, or ſuffrage: So <hi>Stephen</hi> in his Treaſure of the Greek tongue renders it to make or create by ſuffrage. See <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> afterwards.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For reaſons 1. The Officers are given for the good of the Church, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4, 11, 12. therefore ſhe may in a certaine and ordinary way procure them, which yet in many caſes ſhe cannot do, if ſhe have not right to chuſe them. 2. They are given to the Church, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.21, 22. therefore ſhe hath a right to call them to her ſelfe: If ſhe depended upon either Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate or Patron, or any other for a right to call her Officers, they were then rather given to them on whom ſhe ſhould ſo depend, then to her. 3. Otherwiſe the Church, <hi>ſc.</hi> the company of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeevers ſhould be in a worſe condition then any Society as to the ſetling of her ſelfe in her beſt ſtate; no people without rulers over them and Officers for their good but may ſettle ſuch a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themſelves, as the experience of all Common-wealths ſhews 4. In this choyce of the faithfull is laid the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of greater love betwixt the people and their Officers, and ſo the miniſtry of the Officers becomes more fruitfull. 5. The faithful are to hear the true Teachers, to ſhun the falſe, to try the ſpirits, which imports 1. Morall ability for chuſing; 2. A right of chuſing or applying themſelves to the true Miniſters; add to theſe, Chriſtian practiſe and experience; what faithfull ſoule makes any ſcruple of leaving a faithleſſe and unedifying Miniſter at home, to go abroad for enjoying a faithfull and edifying mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry? which yet might not be allowed if Chriſtians had not a right to chuſe their own Officers.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For teſtimonies, 1. Of the ancient Church, <hi>Cyprian</hi> who lived a great light of the Church, about 240 yeares more or leſſe after Chriſt, is plentifull herein.</p>
               <p>As in the Scripture teſtimonies it appears, ſo in thoſe times ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, and ſo in the reformed Churches, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dination of Officers ſucceeded their Election. Hence <hi>Cyprian</hi> to the Presbyters, Deacons and all the people, in the Ordination of miniſters [Moſt dear brethren, we are alwayes wont to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe with you, and to weigh the manners and merits of every one by Common Counſel] <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 33. according to <hi>Pamelius</hi> Edition at the beginning.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> to the people, to avoid the faction of <hi>Feliciſſimus</hi>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:64467:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>and five Presbyters ſiding with him; ſpeaking of them <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 40.</p>
               <p>They mindfull of their conſpiracy, —againſt my Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy, (Epiſcopacy diſtinct from Presbytery had then place in the Church, though of a far purer ſtamp then our Prelacy<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) nay againſt your ſuffrage, (or Election by vote,) and the judgement of God, renew their old oppoſition, &amp;c. he juſtifies his own ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding by the peoples choice of him; to the ſame purpoſe upon the occaſion he ſpeaks <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> to <hi>Antonianus</hi> a brother, about <hi>Cornelius</hi> choſen Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> by the people and the miniſtery. And <hi>Novatian</hi> ſeeking to make himſelfe Biſhop, <hi>Cornelius</hi> is thus juſtified; that he was made Biſhop by the judgement of God and Chriſt; by the Teſtimony of almoſt all the miniſtery, by the vote or ſuffrage of the people then preſent, &amp;c. Here was the miniſters teſtimony, but the choice the peoples. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 52. the ſame <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nelius</hi> he juſtifies againſt <hi>Novatian,</hi> and that with the concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent judgement of a councel aſſembled upon the ſame ground, the ſuffrage of the miniſtry and people. <hi>Epiſt</hi> 67.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> to the miniſtry of <hi>Spaine. Cyprian</hi> with his fellow-Biſhops aſſembled, praiſeth the miniſtry and people of <hi>Spaine;</hi> that they had by lawful Election placed <hi>Sabinus</hi> and <hi>Felix</hi> in ſtead of <hi>Baſilides</hi> and <hi>Martial,</hi> lapſed Biſhops; we have here moſt pregnant teſtimonies and proofes of the peoples right in chuſing.</p>
               <p>They when they had met together, read letters out of <hi>Spaine,</hi> deſiring their advice; where in anſwer <hi>Cyprian</hi> with the reſt of the Biſhops, firſt urging of how great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> it is that the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Biſhop be holy, he thus ſpeaks further; Wherefore it behoves that with full diligence and ſincere tryall they be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen to the miniſtery, who are ſuch as God may heare their Prayers. Neither let the people flatter themſelves as though they might be free from guilt, communicating with a ſinful mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter or Biſhop, and affording their conſent to the unjuſt and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull Epiſcopacy or miniſtery of him that is ſet over them. A little after, Therefore the people obeying the Lords Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and fearing God, ought to ſeparate themſelves from a ſinful Church ruler, neither mixe themſelves at the ſacrifices of a ſacrilegious Prieſt, foraſmuch as they have the greateſt pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:64467:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>either of chuſing the worthy Prieſts (that was the language of thoſe times for Biſhops or Miniſters,) or refuſing the unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, which thing we ſee alſo to deſcend from divine authority, that the Biſhop or Miniſter be choſen, the people being preſent, in the ſight of all, and be approved worthy and fit by publicke judgement and teſtimony, as in <hi>Numb.</hi> 20.26, 27, 28. adde <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vit.</hi> 8.3. &amp;c. God commands the Prieſt to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> before the whole Aſſembly; that is, he teacheth and ſheweth that Ordination of Prieſts ought not to be, but with the joynt knowledge of the people aſſiſting, the people being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, either that the crimes of the evil may be diſcovered, or that the merits of the good may be declared; and it may be a juſt and lawfull Ordination, which hath been examined by the ſuffrage and judgement of all; he ſtill goes on; which thing af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards is obſerved according to divine Precepts in the Acts of the Apoſtles, when <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks to the People about ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Biſhop in the place of <hi>Judas, Acts</hi> 1.15. (<hi>Cyprian</hi> he un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtands thoſe one hundred and twenty names, the people of the Church, and makes uſe of this place for the peoples Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;) he addes, and we take notice the Apoſtles obſerved this, that not only in the Ordination of Prieſts, (that is Biſhops or Miniſters) but of Deacons alſo, <hi>Acts</hi> 6.2, 3. which verily was therefore ſo diligently and warily done, the whole people be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing called together, leſt ſome unworthy ſhould have crept in; &amp;c. he addes that it is moſt diligently to be kept, from divine tradition and Apoſtolicall obſervation, which among them, and almoſt throughout all the Provinces is obſerved, that for the right celebrating Ordinations, all the next Biſhops of the ſame Province meet with that people to whom the Ruler is to be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained; and the Biſhop being choſen, the people being preſent, &amp;c. —which we find obſerved by you (ſaith he) in the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of <hi>Sabinus,</hi> that the office of a Biſhop was conferred up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him by the ſuffrage of the whole brotherhood, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops who were preſent, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 68. This teſtimony is cleare and full for many things worthy our obſervation. 1. That Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation was after Election. 2. That the people have right of chu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the higheſt officers in the Church. 3. That they have the greateſt power of chuſing or refuſing. 4. That they have right, and it is their duty to ſeparate themſelves from ſuch as having
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:64467:18"/>been placed over them prove wicked. 5. That all this is by divine authority. 6. That they have the ſame right to chuſe all Church-officers. 7. That this is the way to keep out the unworthy; whence we may conclude the people owned for true matter of the Church then, were an underſtanding and holy people. <hi>Pameli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> in his Annotations upon the place, though no great friend to the peoples power here, yet proves the preſence and ſuffrage of the people for ſome ages after in <hi>Africa, Auguſtines</hi> Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors ſo choſen; the ſame practice in <hi>Greece</hi> in <hi>Chryſoſtomes</hi> times, in <hi>Spaine,</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and this cuſtome to have continued till <hi>Gregorie</hi> the firſt, nay till the times of <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Lewis</hi> Emperours; the like teſtimony from the firſt times of all immediately ſucceeding the Apoſtles, <hi>Clemens Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manus</hi> (the ſame who is mentioned <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.3.) writing an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle to the Corinthians and taxing a great ſchiſme among them, caſting off ſome of their faithfull miniſters, he tels them it is an unjuſt thing to remove them from their publick mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry, who had been placed by the Apoſtles, or after them by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men, the whole Church conſenting, or it ſeeming good to the whole Church, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Teſtimonies of our Reformers; it is well known to be the doctrine of the reformed Churches generally; I ſhal give an inſtance or two. <hi>Calvin</hi> upon that word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. they two ſaith he, <hi>viz. Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> created the Elders, but the whole multitude as it was the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the Grecians in their Elections, declared with their hands lifted up whom they would have. So the Romane Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians ſpeak many times; the Conſuls who held the Aſſemblies created new Magiſtrates, for no other reaſon, but becauſe they received the votes, and moderated the people in their choice. <hi>Inſtitu. l.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 3. <hi>Sect.</hi> 15. Againe <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> are ſaid to chuſe the Elders; do they this as a duty proper to them? nay rather they permit the matter to the votes of all; therefore in ordaining Paſtors the choice of the people was free; but leaſt any thing ſhould be done tumultuouſly, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> have the leading plaes or rule them as Moderatours; and ſo ought the decree of the Councell of <hi>Laodicea</hi> to be underſtood, which forbids the choyce to be left to the people. <hi>Calv. in Acts</hi> 14.23. <hi>Beza</hi> upon the ſame place, this word (tranſlated, ordained,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:64467:19"/>but ſignifying as formerly we heard, to chuſe by hands lifted up) ariſeth (ſaith he) from the cuſtome of the Grecians, who gave in their votes and ſuffrages with their hands ſtretched out; And the force of this word is to be obſerved, (he ſtill goes on) that we may know <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> did nothing of their owne pleaſure, nor exerciſed any Tyranny in the Church. Then maintaining his owne calling and the calling of the reſt of the Reformers to their miniſtry, Firſt he denies that Ordination or Conſecration by Impoſition of hands to be lawfull, which is uſed among the Papiſts, upon a double ground. 1. Becauſe there was no lawfull choyce before it. 2. Becauſe the Ordainers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong them deſerve excommunication, and in theſe two caſes Ordination is void by the Canons they boaſt of. Secondly he layes down the certaine notes of their call, (his owne with the other miniſters of the Reformation,) that they were approved of both for life and doctrine, by the lawfull Teſtimony of their Churches, that they were by them choſen, and laſtly with calling upon the name of God confirmed in their mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bucer.</hi> The Holy Ghoſt requires, that they who are ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the Holy miniſtery, be firſt tryed and proved, and ſo farre as is poſſible approved to all in the Church; and this he argues from the unfruitfulnes of the miniſtry otherwiſe;—adds; wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and not according to humane wiſedome only, but divine, did <hi>Leo</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Rome</hi> write, that no reaſon would admit, that he that ſhould take care of the Church, ſhould not be both proved &amp; deſired by that very Church,—which <hi>Paul</hi> conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (<hi>viz.</hi> how much it made for the fruit of his miniſtry,) la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours ſo earneſtly to preſerve his love and eſteem among the Corinthians, and to reſtore the ſame among the Galatians. <hi>Bucer.</hi> of the lawful Ordination of Miniſters, <hi>p.</hi> 242.</p>
               <p>Furthermore great care is to be had of this, that thoſe mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters may be given to the Churches, whom they may love, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteem and honour; and that this may be brought to paſſe, no man at all is to be admitted to the ſacred miniſteries of the Church, who is not before religiouſly tryed and approved to the whole Church where he ought to adminiſter, <hi>p.</hi> 243. <hi>p.</hi> 244.</p>
               <p>In this tryall of thoſe that are preſented to the ſervices of the Church, not only is this to be required who are made fit for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:64467:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>thoſe miniſteries by God, but likewiſe that they may be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged, received and accounted ſuch, by the Churches, their tryall is ſo to be ordered and carryed thorough, that it may be knowne and throughly beheld by the whole Church to which any one is to ſerve, who are to be received by them, as given and ſent of the Lord unto them: who are to be refuſed by them, as not given and ſent by the Lord unto them; And then he brings in that of <hi>Cyprian</hi> formerly mentioned. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 68. Let theſe ſuffice for inſtance.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But the people are ignorant, irreligious, and many wayes unfit.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For their abilities in learning, for their judgement in the higheſt and myſterious moſt points, and the like, who are to be choſen, they are by learned Miniſters (where it may be) to be tryed. 2. There is a great uſe of the guidance and direction of able and approved Miniſters, for ordering the proceeding in the choice, that it be done with due care and peaceableneſſe. 3. The People of the Church are not to be ſuppoſed ignorant, irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, &amp;c. they that are ſo are no true matter of the Church, nor to be owned, as formerly this hath been proved; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> this very right and duty of the People addes a further proof, becauſe it belongs to them to chuſe their officers, therefore they muſt not be ſuch a People, and in all theſe teſtimonies we find them ſuppoſed of another ſtampe. 4. Suppoſe that aſſiſtance of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters cannot be had, as in caſe God ſhould enlighten with his truth a company of people in the midſt of <hi>Rome,</hi> might not they by divine charter ſettle among themſelves a miniſtery? In other caſes, when the helpe of miniſters cannot be had, the reaſons formerly given, eſpecially the firſt, ſecond, third and fifth will conclude the Peoples right without them. Otherwiſe this would further enſue after a generall Apoſtacy, as that of the Papacy, though God ſhould enlighten never ſo many Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, except withall he ſhould enlighten ſome of their Prieſts, there muſt be an impoſſibility of Church-Reformation. 5. Though ſuch a concurrence of miniſters, where it may be had, is for the help of the Church, as in the reſpects above na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, yet may they not deveſt her of this native right, to put upon her any but whom ſhe ſhall chuſe and approve.</p>
               <p>It is true, to a wicked People no true matter of the Church,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:64467:20"/>a miniſter may be ſent to preach the Goſpel, though they hate him, (ſo farre from chuſing him;) but it is one thing to be a Preacher to a People, another to be their Paſtor, and ruling elder in way of diſcipline; Only the Saints (viſible) combined, are capable of Paſtorall and diſciplinary intereſt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> How is this right of the people preſerved, to be judged by officers of their own chuſing, in the ordinary way of the Claſſis, when the ſentence ſhall be carried againſt an whole Congregation, by officers of other Congregations, never cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by them? how? was it not fairlier preſerved in the way of primitive Epiſcopacy? All the people chuſing the Biſhop and all the Miniſters. <hi>Cyprian Epiſt.</hi> 68. <hi>ſupr.</hi> So <hi>Clemens</hi> for the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters. <hi>Supr.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. The fourth Inſtruction. <hi>Chriſt hath committed the power of Diſcipline, not to the Officers alone, but to the Church, that is, to the Officers and the brotherhood.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is in the Church of Chriſt a twofold power; of
<list>
                     <item>Order.</item>
                     <item>Office.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>The power of order ariſeth from Church-fellowſhip, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the brethren ſo joyned together.</p>
               <p>The power of office ariſeth from Commiſſion for rule; and belongeth to officers ſet over the brethren.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:64467:20"/>
The power of Order is
<list>
                     <item>To be exerciſed by the brotherhood, whileſt yet without Officers; and it is the power of chuſing their Officers formerly ſpoken to.</item>
                     <item>To be exerciſed by the brotherhood toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the officers; and it is the power of Diſcipline in
<list>
                           <item>
                              <note n="*" place="margin">
                                 <hi>Or binding by Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, for which Admonition makes way; withdrawing partly makes way for it, partly followes upon it.</hi>
                              </note>
                              <hi>Binding</hi> by
<list>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Admonition.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Withdrawing.</hi>
                                 </item>
                                 <item>
                                    <hi>Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</hi>
                                 </item>
                              </list>
                           </item>
                           <item>
                              <hi>Looſing;</hi> or <hi>Abſolution.</hi>
                           </item>
                        </list>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The power of Order is here ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken in a ſenſe very different from that School uſe, where it is diſtinguſhed from juriſdiction, or rather againſt it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Admonition</hi> in caſe a Brother ſinne ſcandalouſly; <hi>Withdrawing,</hi> in caſe he hear not the <hi>Admonition; Excommunication,</hi> in caſe of ſtubborne perſiſting in his ſinne againſt the <hi>Admonition</hi> of the <hi>Church.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Excommunication expreſt by
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Judging.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Putting away.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Taking away.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Purging out.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Delivering to Satan.</hi> 1 Cor. 5.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Stating among the Heathen.</hi> Matth. 18.17.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Looſing or Abſolution in the Churches
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Forgiving.</hi> Upon Repentance 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Comforting.</hi> Upon Repentance 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Confirming her love.</hi> Upon Repentance 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.7, 8.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>This power of Diſcipline, is one of the Keyes of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven: The Key is twofold, of
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Doctrine,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Diſcipline;</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list> Luk. 11.52 and here the opening and ſhutting of the Key is the ſame with binding and looſing formerly. <hi>Matth.</hi> 16.19. with <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17, 18.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="34" facs="tcp:64467:21"/>
The power of diſcipline thus briefly declared, we now come to confirme the inſtruction, that not to the officers alone, but to the Church it is committed, that is the brotherhood with the officers.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It belongs to the Church, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. but the Church never ſignifies the officers alone, throughout the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment frequently the officers and brethren together: as in the inſcriptions of the Epiſtles to the Church at <hi>Corinth, &amp;c.</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times the people diſtinct from their officers; when they were poſſeſſed of officers, <hi>Acts</hi> 15.4. the Church there diſtinct from the Officers whether Apoſtles or Elders, and this Church the brethren, <hi>v.</hi> 22, 23. ſo <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.20. the ſtarres are the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters, and the candleſticks are the Churches; before they were poſſeſſed of officers, <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. there is the Church as the candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, before the candle be put into it. If any man ſhall ſay that in <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.17. the Church ſignifies the officers alone, in ſtead of proving he begs the queſtion.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Apoſtle enjoyning the exerciſe of this power for
<list>
                     <item>Binding, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.</item>
                     <item>Looſing. 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.</item>
                  </list> aſcribes it to the brotherhood together with the officers.</p>
               <p>Firſt, for <hi>Binding,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. he writes to the whole Church. 1. To the ſame here, to whom he inſcribes the Epiſtle, but he inſcribes it to all the Saints in <hi>Corinth,</hi> with all in every place, as com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehended in his ſalutation, and concerned in the inſtitutions of this Epiſtle, though particularly ſent to the Church at <hi>Corinth.</hi> 2. The ſame who were puffed up when they ſhould have mourn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, <hi>v.</hi> 2. are to be gathered together in the name, and with the power of Chriſt, <hi>Pauls</hi> ſpirit joyning with them, though he was abſent in body, <hi>v.</hi> 4. to deliver ſuch an one to Satan, <hi>v.</hi> 5.3. The ſame whoſe glorying is rebuked, the whole lump lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vened, <hi>v.</hi> 6. are to purge out that leaven, <hi>v.</hi> 7. whence the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle digreſſeth from publick leaven, the ſcandalous ſinner, to perſonall leaven, malice and wickedneſſe, <hi>v.</hi> 8.4. The ſame to whom he gives direction for avoiding familiar ſociety with a ſcandalous brother, interpreting the meaning of a former E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtle, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10, 11. they are to judge of thoſe within, <hi>v.</hi> 12. and put away from among themſelves that wicked perſon, <hi>v.</hi> 13.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:64467:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Secondly for looſing, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. the ſame whom he had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly made heavy, <hi>v.</hi> 1, 2. by rebuking in the former Epiſtle, that from their obedience and repentance, he might have much joy of them, when he ſhould come to them, <hi>v.</hi> 3, 4. whom in part he clears <hi>v.</hi> 5. They are the many by whom the inceſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Perſon was rebuked <hi>v.</hi> 6. and they are to forgive and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him, <hi>v</hi> 7.8. The ſame to whom the Apoſtle wrote to make proof of their obedience, <hi>v.</hi> 9. with whom as he formerly joyned in binding, ſo now in looſing, <hi>v.</hi> 10 they are ſtil the ſame, whom formerly he had made heavy, and in whom now he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyced, <hi>cap.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 8. to the end. He that can now caſt ſuch a miſt, as ſhall darken ſo faire and cleare a context, and make us meet with the officers only in all this, miſſing the People, I ſhall allow him this teſtimony, he hath profited very well in the ſchool of darkneſſe. Some footſtep of the Peoples power here we had in the ruines of diſcipline by the Prelates, in that the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved Party was wont to aske the Congregation forgive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Every brother hath a power, and his duty it is to admoniſh firſt ſingly, then jointly before a witneſſe or two, the caſe ſo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring, and there is waight in that admonition for gaining a brother, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.15, 16. how comes it to paſſe, that after the offence is brought to the officers, there is no waight in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick admonition, and conſequently cenſure of the whole brotherhood.</p>
               <p>The end of the Cenſure is to ſhame and humble the ſinner, and is there no waight in the ſolemne judgement of any, nor all the brotherhood, but only of the officers for this end?</p>
               <p n="4">4. If this judgement belong only to the officers, then Chriſt hath ſo inſtituted this Ordinance, as many times it cannot ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine its end, without the ſin of the Church; this is cleare thus; in caſe the Church or brotherhood apprehend the ſentence un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>righteous, they cannot without ſin withdraw from him; the Party ſentenced, (ſuppoſe by officers proceeding as wickedly, as ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times our Prelates and their creatures were wont to do, paſſing ſentence of excommunication for refuſing impious Ceremonies, or the like,) if they ſhal not withdraw, the end is not obtained, the ſentence not obeyed; but to ſay that Chriſt hath ſo inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted this or any other Ordinance, is to taxe his wiſedome and holineſſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="36" facs="tcp:64467:22"/>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Suppoſe ſome few apprehend the ſentence unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, what ſhall they do?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Modeſtly declare their diſſent, and for their parts forbeare to act it.</p>
               <p n="5">5. That the Church (or brotherhood) hath ſome ſhare in the power of the keyes, appears by her honourable relation to Chriſt; the Elders are ſtewards, but the Church is his wife.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> That is the univerſall Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſ.</hi> Every particular Church or company of combined Saints hath the whole nature of the univerſall Church, and the ſame re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to Chriſt, that all the Saints together have, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.27.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Then women and children ſhould ſhare in the power of the keyes, for they are of the Church of beleevers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This is a moſt trifling objection, 1. It is granted by many who make this Objection, that the brethren have right to chuſe their officers, who yet deny women and children any ſhare therein. 2, A power may belong to ſuch an Order, yet not to all in that Order; the Lords Supper belongs to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of beleevers, not to officers only; the children of beleevers are in Church-account beleevers, yet the ſupper belongs not to them. I will adde, that honour which belongs to ſuch an Order, reflects upon them in that order, who are yet debarred Perſonal application; the honour of circumciſion, ſealing up the Jews into Gods family, had reflection upon their women; they were of the circumciſion in oppoſition to the Gentiles, who were the uncircumciſion, though they could not be circumciſed; it is a priviledge and honour of our Nobility in <hi>England,</hi> that they make one Houſe of Parliament; and who can deny that the wives and children of Nobles are concerned in this Honour, though it belongs not to them to ſit in the Houſe?</p>
               <p>Let us now adde the teſtimonies firſt of the primitive, and then of the reformed Churches in ſome of their choiceſt Divines. 1. For the primitive times, <hi>Cyprian,</hi> To the Presbyters and Deacons;</p>
               <p>As for that which my fellow Presbyters, <hi>Donatus</hi> and <hi>Fortu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus, Novatus</hi> and <hi>Gordius</hi> wrote about, I could write nothing in anſwer, foraſmuch as I have determined from the beginning of my Epiſcopacy, to do nothing of mine owne mind, or by
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:64467:22"/>mine own ſentence, without your counſell and the conſent of my people. But when I ſhall come to you, <hi>(he was now in exile,)</hi> by the grace of God we will then deale about thoſe things in common, which either are done, or are to be done, as mutuall honour requires, <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 6. at the end. The like to this, in the 18. Epiſtle, about the demand of ſome of the lapſed, (that is thoſe who had fallen in time of Perſecution,) deſiring to be reſtored, having for that end obtained the Confeſſors letters, (the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors were ſuch as were impriſoned for the truth.) This thing (ſaith he) ſince it belongs to the counſell and ſentence of us all, I would not judge it beforehand, neither dare I challenge to my ſelfe alone a common buſineſſe.</p>
               <p>When ſome Presbyters had over-haſtily received ſome of the lapſed to the Lords Supper, <hi>He tels them they muſt make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count to plead their cauſe before himſelfe, the reſt of the Miniſters, the Confeſſors, and the whole People.</hi> Epiſt. 10.</p>
               <p>When he yet in exile was conſulted with by letters by his Presbyters about certaine who had fallen, and were now retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, deſirous to be received againe of the Church, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwers;</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I cannot be judge alone in this caſe; many of the miniſters are ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and this caſe requires exact handling, not only with my fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low miniſters, but with the whole People; for the thing is to be weighed with well-poiſed moderation, and ſo to be ſentenced, as may for after times ſettle an example about the miniſters of the Church,</hi> Epiſt. 28.</p>
               <p>The miniſtery of <hi>Rome</hi> to <hi>Cyprian,</hi> (<hi>there being at this time no Biſhop at</hi> Rome,) <hi>In this great buſineſſe it ſeemed good to us, which thou alſo haſt formerly handled, that the Peace of the Church be upheld; furthermore, ſo conference of counſels being had with the Biſhops, Presbyters, Deacons, Confeſſors, and in like manner with the ſtanding People to handle the cauſe of the lapſed,</hi> Epiſt. 31.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Cyprian</hi> to the People, concerning <hi>Feliciſſimus</hi> and the five Presbyters of his faction; <hi>By the Providence of God they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go the puniſhment they have deſerved, that not being caſt out by us, they ſhould caſt out themſelves; —According to your divine ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frages, conſpirators and wicked men ſhould of their owne accord drive themſelves out of the Church;</hi> (he here cals the ſuffrage of
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:64467:23"/>the people divine, not becauſe infallible, but becauſe it is ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to Scripture that they ſhould have their vote) Againe, <hi>They alone beare the puniſhment of their conſpiracy, who formerly according to your ſuffrages, now according to the judgements of God, have deſerved to undergo the ſentence of their conſpiracy and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſeneſſe.</hi> To the ſame People; about the buſineſſe of the lapſed in generall for receiving or ſtill refuſing them. Cyprian decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his hope ſhortly to be reſtored together with his fellow mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters; <hi>Whom being preſent,</hi> (ſaith he <hi>according to your iudgement either way,</hi> (arbitrium,) <hi>likewiſe, and the Common Counſell of us all, we may order and exactly handle the things that are to be done, as once it ſeemed good,</hi> Epiſt. 40. A further Teſtimony we have formerly ſet down at the end of the ninth Argument, for the matter of the Church; ſhewing at once how the People of the Church were qualified, and what power they had for keeping out the unworthy. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 55. More Teſtimonies of like nature might be alledged out of the ſame father, but theſe ſhall ſuffice.</p>
               <p>I ſhall not need here to obſerve, how he aſcribes to the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in point of cenſure, as their right; counſell, conſent, vote or ſuffrage, judgement either way, or <hi>arbitrium,</hi> nor how generall his Teſtimonies are, as including the reſt of the miniſtry; the miniſtry of <hi>Rome</hi> likewiſe giving the like Teſtimony.</p>
               <p>We come now to ſome few Teſtimonies out of ſome of the choyceſt Divines of the Reformed Churches. <hi>Calvin, Let us ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve that this temper is to be held in excommunication, that this diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline be exerciſed by the Common Councell of the Elders, and with the conſent of the People, and this is the remedy whereby Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny is prevented, in</hi> 1 Cor. 5.4. <hi>That is the warrantable proceeding in excommunication which</hi> Paul <hi>ſhews, if not only the Elders do it apart, but with the knowledge and approbation of the Church,</hi> viz. <hi>in that manner that the multitude of the People do not rule the action, but obſerve it as a witneſſe and keeper, that nothing be done by a few at their pleaſure.</hi> Inſtitut. lib. 4. cap. 12. ſect. 7.</p>
               <p>Bucer. <hi>This power (of the keyes,) is in the whole Church, but the authority of the miniſtry is in the Elders and Biſhops, as of old at</hi> Rome <hi>the Power was in the People, the authority in the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, in</hi> Mat. 16.18, 19. The ſame Author expounding, <hi>Matth.</hi>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:64467:23" rendition="simple:additions"/>18.15. <hi>&amp;c. If the offending brother heare not the ſecond admoniti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, let his ſtubbornneſſe be declared to the Church, that he may be the third time admoniſhed by the whole Congregation, of thoſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt whom he is, or whereof he is a part; and if he heare not the Church, being admoniſhed by her, let him be accounted as an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then and Publicane.</hi> Againe: <hi>of the Power of binding and looſing, that is of ſhutting out, or receiving into the Church, whether at the beginning or after wickedneſſe committed, I have ſpoken before; Mat.</hi> 16. but here it is clearly ſet forth that this power, that is, the keyes of the kingdome of heaven, is in the hands of all thoſe who meet together in the name of Chriſt, that is in faith; becauſe theirs is the ſpirit of the Lord and his word; for ſuch only meet in the name of Chriſt, that is, truſting upon Chriſt, and grow together many members into one body, &amp;c. Then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreting the 19. <hi>v.</hi>—when two of you ſhal agre together to ask any thing, &amp;c. he thus ſpeaks of private admonition, and abſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the hands of the brethren; the Lord ſpeaks here eſpecially of praying for pardon on their behalfe who had offended. Hence therefore we may learne the fruit of private admonition and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution; for if two ſhall agree together, to beg the pardon of a ſin; that ſin muſt be known to them both, and acknowledged as a ſin, here therefore the private admonition, or confeſſion of that ſin muſt have had place. Now foraſmuch as true prayer ſhuts out doubting of obtaining, it muſt needs be that a brother may confirme a brother, that pardon is granted, and by apply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it to him, may render him ſecure in the Lord; hence the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren in private, according to Chriſts inſtitution, exerciſe in part the power of the keyes, and thence their right of publick exerciſe of them, it being of the ſame kind, wil evidently follow, as he there ſpeaks. <hi>It is true,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Lord hath uttered this Promiſe concerning a few, that he might teach how he approves and embraceth us, agreeing and conſenting together in him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, though we be never ſo ſmall a number; but we ſhall pleaſe him more, if many amongſt our ſelves ſhall agree together in him, and we ſhall be able to doe things innumerable in his name.</hi> The ſame Author. <hi>The Apoſtle blames the Corinthians, that the whole Church had not appointed mourning, that is, faſting and publick deprecation of the wrath of God for this wickedneſſe, and that ſhe had not caſt out the inceſtuous Perſon out of her Communion,—He
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:64467:24"/>did no loſſe ſolemnely exhort the Corinthians, that after his repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, they would receive him into the favour of the Lord and his Church,</hi> lib. de regno Chriſti c. 9. p. 43. There is much more in the ſame grave Author to the ſame purpoſe up and down in his works; I ſhall adde only one ſhort teſtimony more out of <hi>Peter Martyr. We conclude</hi> ſaith he <hi>without the conſent of the Church, (that is the People of the Congregation,) no man can be excommunicated.</hi> loc. com. de excommunicat. ſent. 9. <hi>This right belongs to the Church, neither ought it to be taken from her</hi> ſent 10.</p>
               <p>We ſhall forbeare further quotations, it being generally the doctrine of the Reformers, as is well known to ſuch as are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with their Writings.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI.</head>
               <p>THis Chapter ſhall be taken up with certaine Concluſions, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon the former about diſcipline.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As the Prelates, ſtripping both the People and the El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders of the power of diſcipline, violate the Goſpe-order in two maine degrees, (we may adde a third, in that they take it into their owne hands who have nothing to do with it,) ſo they that will have the Presbyterian Government ſo exerciſed, as all pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſhall be confined to the Elders excluding the People, vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late the Goſpell-order in one maine degree at the leaſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Foraſmuch as the People of the Church have a power of Church-order for the exerciſe of diſcipline, both privately and publickly, hence we may now clearly ſee of what neceſſity it is, that the matter of the Church be only viſible Saints according to the doctrine and explication of the matter of the Church formerly laid downe. Many there are, who looſing this Peg in the Tabernacle of the Peoples power for diſcipline, they then looſe another, concerning their qualification for the due matter of the Church, and thence a third, their right of chuſing officers, and a fourth, the due limits for the Sacraments, and ſo the whole frame growes ruinous, I much admire the wiſedome of our king and lawgiver of his Church, who hath ſo ordered all,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:64467:24"/>as where his Patterne is obſerved, there muſt be a beautifull Temple; To inſtance in this particular, becauſe the People have their ſhare in the power of the keyes, and the exerciſe of it: therefore they muſt be a knowing and a holy People, without which they have no Principles for ſuch duties. 2. Had this been obſerved, Prelacy had never got footing in the Churches. 3. Much leſſe Primacy over all, that which the man of ſinne claims to his pretended chaire; the ſlacking of this joint made way for the myſtery of iniquity in the world, and the infirming of it muſt make for the deſtruction thereof.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In ſetling a diſciplinary Congregation, there is the ſubſtance of a Church-Covenant, whether in word expreſt or not. What is the ſubſtance of a Church-Covenant? The mutuall conſent of the faithful for walking together in one Congregation, according to the rules of the Goſpel, for faith, obedience, communion in Worſhip and Diſcipline; in ſetling the Church in her Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions: here is the ſubſtance of this, theſe things are viſibly done; what objection then can there be of weight againſt the ſolemne profeſſion of it by word? 1. The Scripture ſeemes to hold it forth, as <hi>Iſa</hi> 44 5. So Iſrael of old was taken into Covenant, and how often the Covenant renewed with them, even upon ſingular reformations. 2. In the Primitive times the <hi>Catechumens</hi> when received into Church fellowſhip, gave up themſelves by ſolemne profeſſion openly expreſt unto the Church. 3. When members are admitted in the reformed Churches, they profeſſe their purpoſe for religions walking in Church-fellowſhip, and for ſubjection to the Diſcipline. 4. In this, as in other caſes, by open profeſſion and covenanting, we lay a ſtricter tye upon our ſelves, for all duties of Church-communion. 5. We do more expreſſely witneſſe our high eſteeme of Gods inſtitution for Church-order and priviledges,</p>
               <p>This confederacy according to the order of the Goſpel, ſeems to give immediate right to the ſealing Ordinances, as viſible inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt in the Covenant of grace gives the firſt right.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It was not intereſt in the Covenant of grace alone that gave immediate right to Circumciſion, and the Paſſeover of old, but there muſt be a profeſt joyning with the Church of the Jews in her Diſcipline and Policie; therefore <hi>Job</hi> (for inſtance,) was not to be circumciſed, becauſe not ſo adjoyn'd.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="42" facs="tcp:64467:25"/>
2. Where there is full communion in Church-priviledges, there muſt be the exerciſe of Diſcipline for keeping that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion pure, under paine of higheſt diſpleaſure from the Lord, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>throughout;</hi> but where there is communion in the ſealing Ordinances, there is full communion in Church priviledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; therefore there muſt be this reall confederacy for diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
               <p n="3">3. If the ſealing Ordinances may (at leaſt ordinarily) be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtred to ſuch as refuſe confederacy for diſcipline, then may the Ordinance of diſcipline for ever be refuſed by the Churches: but this may not be, as hath more largely been proved. <hi>Inſtruct.</hi> 2. <hi>cap.</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>To me (ſaith grave and learned <hi>Bucer,</hi>) the Church without the moſt frequent uſe of mutual admonition,
<note place="margin">Mat. 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ct. 4. p. 386</note> ſeems the ſame with a kingdome that is without judgement, without the uſe of laws, and as a city brought indeed under the Power of the Prince, but as yet not ſo orderd and ſetled by him, as that it ſhould have the forme of a city and of a Common-wealth, Magiſtracy being put upon it, and laws ſetled; thus he; and what authentick right can there be of publick adminiſtring the peculiar Priviledges of the Common-wealth, to the free borne ſubjects in a city ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſetled? ſo for the Church undiſciplined.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Thoſe baptized by <hi>John,</hi> and the Eunuch by <hi>Philip.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> When the time or the place was not for particular Churches, the firſt right alone ſufficient, as before the Temple or Tabernacle, ſacrifices not confined to place.</p>
               <p n="4">4. <hi>Concluſion.</hi> For ſetling diſcipline in this Kingdome, Perſon unfit for Church-Communion are to be left out.</p>
               <p>This queſtion, (whether for the true method of ſetling of Chriſt the Churches aright in this Kingdome, Perſons unfit are to be left out, or caſt out,) well cleared, will make much for true Reformation among us. To this we ſay two things.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Suppoſing all ſuch are to be caſt out, they muſt firſt be left out, that they may be caſt out, leaving them out orderly making way for their caſting out.</p>
               <p n="1">1. That they may be caſt out, diſcipline muſt be ſetled, for
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:64467:25"/>it is by diſcipline, that they muſt be caſt out; that diſcipline may be ſetled, officers muſt be choſen by the people of the Church; but Perſons unfit for Church-Communion, 1. are not the People of the Church. 2. They are morally unfit to chuſe officers. 3. They are a Party engaged, as if Malefactors ſhould chuſe their Judge; therefore they may not chuſe officers.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The diſcipline for caſting out is to be exerciſed, as by the officers by an office-power, ſo by the people by a Power of Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der; but Perſons fit to be caſt out, may not have this power and the exerciſe of it; this would prevent diſcipline for ever, except we ſhall think that they will caſt out themſelves.</p>
               <p n="3">3. As in a Church where Diſcipline is ſetled, ſuch as are for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mally ſuſpended, or to be ſuſpended, are left out as to vote or conſent before they be caſt out; ſo in a Church to be ſetled, ſuch as are materially ſuſpended, or to be ſuſpended, (as are all to whom we refuſe, or ſhould refuſe the Sacraments) are to be left out, before they be caſt out.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If Chriſtians in name, but ſcandalous in life, have not loſt their diſciplinary intereſt till they be caſt out, then neither have the ſcandalous Miniſters loſt their miniſteriall intereſt for Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline till they be caſt out: if ſo, then theſe Miniſters with thoſe Chriſtians may, joyning together, ſet up the Prelatical Diſcipline Eccleſiaſtically valid. Whether now ſhall theſe be withdrawne from or not, that the true Diſcipline may be ſet up? If not, they will carry the falſe by number of Votes; if they may, the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion is granted, there muſt be leaving out before caſting out.</p>
               <p n="2">2. They are to be left out, not caſt out.</p>
               <p n="1">1. They onely are to be caſt out by Diſcipline in caſe of ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous ſinning, who have beene by voluntary confederacy under it, and accepted as fit matter of the Church; but ſuch were not our ſcandalous ſinners; they were never yet under the Diſcipline which we contend for, neither can they in true account, be owned as fit matter of the Church. 1. That only they who are true matter of the Church are objects of diſcipline, it is cleare, becauſe diſcipine is for them within, not for them without. 2. only them who have by voluntary confederacy come under it. 1. No man, or ſociety of men, hath Church-power over another, without his conſent firſt had: as the reverend Aſſembly ſpeaks
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:64467:26"/>in anſwer to the Diſſenting Brethren; the mutual aſſent and agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the people among whom, and over whom diſcipline is to be exerciſed, is the next foundation of the exerciſe thereof. 2. Diſcipline being among the weapons of ſpirituall warfare, and having to do onely with the conſcience, it hath place only upon thoſe who conſcientiouſly (in appearance at leaſt) have owned this Diſcipline as an ordinance, &amp; therupon, of free accord, volun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tarily engaged in it. <hi>Object.</hi> The preaching the word is to deal only with the conſcience; ſhall it therefore be preached onely to ſuch as voluntarily ſubmit to hearing? <hi>Anſ.</hi> The preaching of the word is an ordinance, firſt proving it ſelfe, and then all other ordinances, as Sacraments, Cenſures; therefore ſo far as it hath firſt convinced, others take place; 3. <hi>The people of the Church are a willing people.</hi> 4. The Diſcipline had no place with the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techumens of old, notwithſtanding their perſonall profeſſion, till upon their voluntary giving up themſelves to the Church, and by the Church approved they were received into full Church fellowſhip. 5. The like method is uſed by the reformed Churches; None are under diſcipline, who have not firſt been approved and by voluntary tender of themſelves received to the Supper.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The Church is ſo to be made up of her members, in her ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall congregations, as that the ſmaller number is ever to be ſuppoſed to be caſt out of the greater; 1. Foraſmuch as the people have their Vote in caſting out; 2. Foraſmuch as the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence and cenſure of thoſe who are to caſt out, make for the humbling and ſhameing of thoſe who are to be caſt out; but if all the ſcandalous are to be caſt out, it cannot be ſuppoſed that they will be the ſmaller number, in ſeverall congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Caſting out ſuppoſeth publique, but perſonall admonition (if he hear not the Church) and particularly proofe of the fault' for which the ſinner is to be caſt out: but how this is poſſible in our Nation, I ſhall only appeal to experience, and common ſenſe.</p>
               <p n="4">4. If all ſcandalous ſinners amongſt us be to be caſt out, then are they all the ſcandalous of the Church, (what have I to do to judge them that are without?) But they are not all the ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous of the Church; with none of the ſcandalous of the Church muſt we familiarly keep company, and yet may we abide
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:64467:26"/>in the world, but with-many of the ſcandalous in the Nation, we muſt upon diverſe occaſions keep familiar company, except we will go out of the world, (and it is the ſame caſe in all Nations of the world). 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.9. with experience.</p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>HENCE,</head>
                  <p>The true way of Reformation amongſt us, in this; that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons fit matter of the Church, joyne together in Church fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, chuſe Officers with Cautions formerly ſaid down, and ſo forme Congregations into a diſciplinary State, exerciſing diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipline among themſelves, leaving out the reſt. From Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionall Churches thus ſetled, Combinations of Churches for mutuall help will ariſe; but here is now our ſcruple about the civill Magiſtrate, what warrant Chriſtians and Miniſters have thus to proceed, except he by publick authority take order. In anſwer to this I lay down</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VII. The ſifth Inſtruction. <hi>There is a Church-Power formally diſtinct from the Civill.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>One concluſion will here be of uſe before we inſiſt upon the proofe of this Inſtruction; And it is this; The authority and relation of Magiſtracy is one and the ſame; whether the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the Magiſtrate be Chriſtian or not; as the authority and relation of a father is one and the ſame, in both caſes; It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the office of Magiſtracy to preſerve authoritatively both Tables of the law of God, to take order that the Subjects may live in godlineſſe and honeſty, though onely the Chriſtian Magiſtrate hath principles for exerciſing this power in a Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an way. This premiſed we come to the proofe.</p>
               <p n="1">1. From the enſignes of theſe Powers; the Sword of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill; the Keyes of the Eccleſiaſticall; theſe, as of different
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:64467:27"/>name and nature, ſo they repreſent that power, whereof they are the enſignes, different.</p>
               <p n="2">2. From the nature of theſe Powers compared 1. In their Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; of the one, the Common-wealth; of the other, the Church. 2. In their laws; of the one, ſuch as humane wiſedome findes neceſſary or expedient, for the ſociety of mankind; of the other, only the word of God. 3. Their authority; of the one, Imperiall, commanding in their own names, as Lawgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers to the Subjects; of the other, miniſterial commanding only in the name of Chriſt, the only Lawgiver of his Church. 4. In their puniſhments &amp; rewards; of the one, ſuch as concern the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward man; as for puniſhments, fines, impriſonment, baniſhment, death, &amp;c. For rewards, revenues, honours, &amp;c. Of the other, ſuch as concerne the inward man; binding or looſing (the wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pons of this warfare are ſpirituall,) retaining or remitting ſins.</p>
               <p n="3">3. From the inſtitution of theſe powers; the inſtitution of Magiſtracy is divine in generall. (The powers that be, are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained of God.) The conſtitution in particular is humane, in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſe nations, diverſe; in ſome, the Governement by the king, in others by the State, in others by the People; (Be ſubject to every humane creation,) 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.13. The inſtitution of Church-office, is divine both generally, that there be officers in the Church, and particularly that theſe be they and no other, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. the civill magiſtrate is nowhere in the liſt, or roll of Church-officers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. From the conveyance of theſe powers. 1. The civill ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrate, (to inſtance in the ſupreme Perſon,) may be by ſucceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; Church-officers muſt be by Election; the civill magiſtrate, (to inſtance in the ſupreme Court,) may be by election of the people of the Common-wealth as ſuch, whether duly qualified for Church-Government or not; Church-officers muſt be by election of the People of the Church as ſuch; and they muſt be qualified according to Scripture-Characters, that they may rightly be choſen.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From the exerciſe of theſe powers; both theſe powers were exerciſed in their full height, for the firſt three hundred years after Chriſt, when yet, neither was any Church-officer a civill magiſtrate, neither did any civill magiſtrate pretend to be a Church-officer.</p>
               <p n="6">
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:64467:27"/>
6. From the diſſolution of theſe powers; excommunicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on diſſolves all Church-power in the hand of a Church-officer, when rightly adminiſtred againſt him; it neither diſſolves nor weakens civill power in the hand of the Magiſtrate, when right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly adminiſtred againſt him.</p>
               <p n="7">7. From the farre diſtance of theſe Powers; a woman may be a civill magiſtrate, (as <hi>Deborah</hi> in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> in <hi>England,</hi>) but a woman may not be a Church-officer; a Perſon may by good right be a Magiſtrate, yet by no right a Church-member, much leſſe a Church-officer.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Adde to theſe the concurrent judgement of all Churches, who have ever avouched both in Doctrine and Practice theſe powers diſtinct.</p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>Hence a CONSECTARY.</head>
                  <p>To the Church, as the Church, it belongs, to exerciſe all Church-power, whether the civill Magiſtrate take order for it or not, whether he allow it or oppoſe it. We ſhall here pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe two concluſions to prevent miſtake.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The civill magiſtrate is not to allow any exerciſe of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power in his dominions, which either is, or by him is conceived to be contrary to the rule of Scripture, and ſo diſpleaſing to God.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. In caſe the Church proceed according to Scripture-rule, and is by the Civill magiſtrate oppoſed or perſecuted, ſhe muſt not defend her ſelfe by armes, but ſuffer in a way of well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doing.</p>
                  <p>This premiſed, now to the Proof of the Conſectary.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. The Church, as the Church, is entruſted with the power of diſcipline, a great Goſpell-Ordinance, in the exerciſe whereof conſiſts a great Part of the adminiſtration of the Mediators Kingdome, as we have ſeen in the ſecond inſtruction formerly; and this power intrinſecally in her, independently upon the civil magiſtrate: therefore it behoves her, as ſhe would be found faithfull in that great truſt committed to her, to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe it.</p>
                  <p>To the Church of beleevers, not yet furniſhedwith officers
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:64467:28"/>in any Congregation, it belongs to chuſe and ſettle officers, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king in what due help of the neighbour Miniſters &amp; Congreg a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions may be had. To the Church miniſteriall, in her Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons furniſhed with Officers, it belongs to exerciſe diſcipline, as occaſion ſhall bee. The ſame right that believers have to joyne together in congregations, for duties of ſolemne worſhip, the ſame right have they for the duties of diſcipline; the ſame right that they have to chuſe Elders for labouring in the word and doctrine, the ſame have they for chuſing Elders that ſhall rule them: the ſame Commiſſion that enjoynes the Paſtors and Teachers to preach and adminiſter the Sacraments, enjoynes them likewiſe to diſpenſe diſcipline, but according to the me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod of the Goſpel.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. The Church when in her pureſt ſtate for the firſt 300 years, durſt no more neglect that ordinance of diſcipline, then any other Goſpel-ordinance, though cruelly perſecuted by the civill powers; here that concluſion is of uſe; The relation and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Magiſtracy is one, &amp;c.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. If that may be laid aſide, the Sacraments muſt; becauſe partaking in them are acts of higheſt Church-fellowſhip, and the Lord allowes not under ſevere penalty upon the whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, the retaining of ſcandalous ſinners in Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, who yet cannot be caſt out, but by the exerciſe of Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pline.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. The civill Magiſtrate muſt not be allowed power to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge Chriſt, of the compleat adminiſtration of his viſible King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, but if the Church ſo depend upon him for the exerciſe of Diſcipline, as without his allowance ſhe hath no right thereto, then is this Power allowed the Magiſtrate.</p>
                  <p n="5">5. The civill Magiſtrate hath a power cumulative for the Churches good, therefore he is promiſed her as a bleſſing; (Kings ſhall be thy nurſing fathers;) not privative of her good; then ſhould he be no bleſſing to her; but if in his power it be to deprive her of the power of Diſcipline and the exerciſe of it, he hath a power privative of her greateſt good, her purity, that which all the peace ſhe can have by his meanes can never re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence; nay this muſt needs deprive her of her peace too, as making way for all wickedneſſe in a ſhort time to overgrow her, and ſo expoſing her to the wrath of God.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:64467:28"/>
There is yet another ſcruple ſticks with ſome, and that is E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy. They who account that Government to be accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Scripture, know not how to indeavour Reformation any other way.</p>
                  <p>To remove this;</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Suppoſing ſuch an Epiſcopacy as we finde to have had place in the Church, about two hundred years (ſuppoſe ſooner) after Chriſt to be according to Scripture. 1. Yet the frame of our Prelacy, made up of civill Lawyers and their retinue, down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, hath no countenance therefrom, but muſt owne the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy as the root whence it ſprang.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. Their adminiſtration was intolerably wicked. 1. Highly ſacrilegious taking out of the hands both of Miniſters and Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, that power which Chriſt hath given to them, and commanded them to uſe in the exerciſe of diſcipline. 2. Noto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly prophane, beſides their whole courſe, abetting prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſtrengthening the hands of the wicked every where; a memorable monument hereof we have in the Book of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, of their procuring and enjoyning, for the moſt abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and ridiculous, (not without palpable ſtraines of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganiſme,) Prophanation of the Lords day; another, the many, moſt ſcandalous and vile of the ſons of men, by them ordained Miniſters, and highly preferred. 3. Groſſely ſuperſtitious, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe the Ceremonies new and old, ſo zealouſly by them con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended for, as if all religion had been in that will-worſhip. 4. Plainly idolatrous; memorable here, their Altar-worſhip. 5. Egregiouſly perſecuting; the voice of bloud ſpeaks here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loud, from Gaoles, from Pillories, even the bloud of the ſincere and godly Party, generally up and down this Kingdome, Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and Chriſtians, continually under the laſh of theſe taske<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſters. Memorable here the many precious ſervants of God, now in new <hi>England,</hi> forced by their tyranny into thoſe remote wilderneſſes. 6. Openly rebellious; ſhaking with both hands all true foundations of civill Governement, under pretence of Prerogative, lawleſſe ones, endeavouring the ſame boundleſſe tyranny in the State Civill, that they themſelves exerciſed in the Church. Memorable here, that Proclamation of their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing and enjoyning, ſo highly abetting and ſtirring up to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, ſet forth againſt the Scots, raiſed up by the hand of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:64467:29"/>to ſtand for the right of civill Governement, as became true Patriots and free Subjects.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. Suitable to their frame and adminiſtration was their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion, ſo farre from comming in at the true doore by Chriſt appointed for entrance into Church office, and accordingly by the Primitive Biſhops made uſe of, to wit, the Peoples Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that they ſcorned to owne this door, but other back-doors did they not ſo much come in, as break in at, ſtiffely avouching this diſorder of theirs.</p>
                  <p n="4">4, It is the right and duty of the Church, to ſeparate from ſinful Church-rulers, as formerly we have ſeen both from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and antiquity; how great a neceſſity was there then of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parating from this whole tribe, whoſe foundation, frame, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration was ſo Apocryphall and Anti-chriſtian?</p>
                  <p>Suppoſing then Epiſcopacy diſtinct from Presbytery, to be according to rule, yet was our Prelacy ſo little of kinred to the ancient Epiſcopacy, and ſo contrary to the rule, as either it muſt not ſtand, or the Churches muſt not ſtand; that we may then come to that, we muſt firſt leave this 2. Come to it in the true way which is the free choyce of the people and Miniſters. That this may be done, the people fit matter of the Church, muſt firſt be form'd into Congregations. As for that which would here fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be required upon this ſuppoſition, Impoſition of hands by Biſhops, in this caſe of ſo great Apoſtacy as hath prevail'd, the neceſſity would ſufficiently plead excuſe: <hi>As ſuppoſe a people cald out of</hi> Babylon, <hi>if impoſition of hands by Popiſh Biſhops might be had for ordaining ſome among them to be their Miniſters, it were not worth the having; but withall it being impoſſible to be had, the call and confirmation of the Church is ſufficient,</hi> as <hi>Beza</hi> pleads for the firſt Reformers, in <hi>Acts</hi> 14.23. But further for clearing this ſcruple, we lay down</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:64467:29"/>
               <head>CHAP. VIII. The ſixth Inſtruction. <hi>That Biſhops in office above Preſbyters, are no Church-officers of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution, it is pleaded by</hi> Jerome <hi>from Scripture, and the higheſt Goſpel-antiquity.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THere is a Divine Biſhop, one and the ſame with a Presbyter or a Paſtor or Teacher of a Congregation, and Elder <hi>labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Word and Doctrine;</hi> there is an humane Biſhop, one that pleads his office to be above the Presbyters or Paſtors office; and two things he challengeth above the Presbyter. 1. Power of Ordination. 2. Power of Juriſdiction. <hi>Jerome</hi> a learned Father, famous about 390 yeeres after Chriſt, in his Epiſtle to <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vagrius,</hi> and in his Commentary upon the Epiſtle to <hi>Titus,</hi> ſpeaks clearly to this queſtion, both from Scripture, and from the firſt Goſpel antiquity; I have therefore thought fit to tranſlate that Epiſtle, and thence to obſerve his Arguments, from Scripture, as likewiſe what he produceth from antiquity, that we might at once give double light to this queſtion, knowing well, that where antiquity is uſed againſt the Scripture it is nothing worth, but whereit ſtands fair with the Scripture, it may be a ſecondary con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation of the true meaning of Scripture, to the impartial enqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter after truth; and an argument fully in force againſt the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary, pretending antiquity for his Error. This Epiſtle is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected againſt a certaine perſon who would have a Deacon to be above a Presbyter, againſt whom thus <hi>Jerome;</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We read in <hi>Iſaiah, the fool will ſpeak folly,</hi> I hear of one who hath broken forth into ſo great folly, that he would prefer Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons before Presbyters, that is before Biſhops. For when the Apoſtle teacheth clearly, that Presbyters are the ſame with Biſhops, who may endure that the ſervant of tables and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowes, ſhould lift up himſelfe ſwollen above them, by whoſe prayers the body and blood of Chriſt is conſecrate? Seekeſt thou authority? Heare the Teſtimony, <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Timothy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Phil. 1.</note> the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>to all the Saints in Chriſt Jeſus which are at Philippi, with the Biſhops and Deacons.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts 20.</note> Wilt thou another ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample? In the <hi>Acts</hi> of the Apoſtles thus, <hi>Paul</hi> writes to the
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:64467:30"/>Miniſters <hi>(Sacerdotes)</hi> of one Church; <hi>Take heed to your ſelves and to the whole flock, over which the holy Ghoſt hath made you Biſhops:</hi> (for it is the ſame word here, that every otherwhere is tranſlated <hi>Biſhops</hi>) <hi>that yee might rule the Church of the Lord,</hi> (ſo he reads it) <hi>which he hath purchaſed with his owne blood.</hi> And that no man may contentiouſly wrangle, that there were many Biſhops in one Church, hear yet another teſtimony, by which it is moſt manifeſtly proved,
<note place="margin">Tit. 1.</note> that a Biſhop and Presbyter are one and the ſame. <hi>For this end I left thee in Creet, that thou mighteſt redreſſe the things that were wanting, that thou migheſt appoint Presbyters in every City, as I have alſo commanded thee; If any man be without blame, the huſband of one wife, have faithful chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.</note> not accuſed of riot, or diſobedient; for it behooves a Biſhop to be without blame, as the Steward of God.</hi> And to <hi>Timothy, Neglect not the grace which is in thee, which was given thee by prophecy, with the laying on of hands of the Preſbytery.</hi> But <hi>Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> likewiſe in his firſt Epiſtle ſaith,
<note place="margin">1 Pet. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>The Elders or Preſbyters which are among you, I intreat, who am your fellow-Elder, and a wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the ſuffrings of Chriſt, and alſo a partaker of glory to come, which is to be revealed, that yee rule the flock of Chriſt, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſee it, not of neceſſity, but willingly, according to God,</hi> which in the Greek is more ſignificantly expreſt, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Biſhoping that is, overſeeing them, from whence the name of Biſhop is drawne.</p>
               <p>Do the teſtimonies of theſe ſo great men ſeem ſmall to thee? let the Goſpel-trumpet ſound, the Son of thunder, whom Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus loved ſo much, who drunk the flowing ſtreams of doctrine out of his Saviours breaſt; <hi>The Presbyter to the elect Lady and to her children, whom I love in the truth.</hi> And in another Epiſtle, <hi>The Presbyter to the wel-beloved</hi> Caius, <hi>whom I love in the truth.</hi> Hitherto <hi>Ierome.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here we have both clearly affirmed, and ſtrongly confirmed, that a Biſhop in office above a Presbyter, is no where to be found in Scripture, but Biſhop and Presbyter are two names of one and the ſame office, ſo that whatſoever belongs to any Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop by vertue of his office, the ſame belongs to every Presbyter, as he is a Presbyter. For clearing both his affirmation and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmation, we muſt obſerve that in his time the cuſtome of the Church, had obtained that ſome were ſingle Presbyters, others
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:64467:30"/>ſo Presbyters, as withall Biſhops challenging above ſingle Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, the Power of Ordination at the leaſt, themſelves like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ordained, not by ſingle Presbyters, (as they called them,) but by Biſhops; and it is pleaded by the Advocates of Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy at this day, that the Apoſtles before their death ordained ſeverall Biſhops, in office above Presbyters, (as formerly we laid down,) over the Churches in ſeverall cities, and theſe Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops in continuall ſucceſſion ordained others; neither can a Biſhop be ordained by Presbyters, nor a presbyter without a Biſhop; at leaſt ordinarily.</p>
               <p>Againſt this <hi>Jerome</hi> pleads, taxing the great errour of them that would preferre a Deacon to a Presbyter, <hi>That it is all one to preferre him to a Biſhop; for according to Scripture, the one is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther greater nor leſſe then the other, neither is there any ſuch diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of ſingle Presbyter from the Biſhop, but they are one and the ſame,</hi> and this he ſaith the Apoſtle teacheth clearly; and having affirmed this, he proves it by many Arguments.</p>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>From the granted operation belonging to the Presbyters of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice as ſuch, and therefore to every Presbyter, which is to conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crate the body and bloud of Chriſt. Where is the higheſt officiall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, there is the higheſt office; but in the hands of every Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter is the higheſt officiall operation: (for we may not thinke that either impoſition of hands in Ordination, or paſſing ſentence in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communication, are acts of higher nature, then conſecrating the ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments in the Supper, and this belongs to every Presbyter by vertue of his office,) therefore in the hands of every Presbyter is the higheſt office.</hi> The like Argument we have. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. <hi>Thoſe acts which are moſt worthy of honour are the higheſt; but ſuch is labour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the word and doctrine, belonging to every miniſter of the word, compared with ruling challenged by the Biſhop.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. Argument from the two firſt teſtimonies, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. and <hi>Acts</hi> 20. <hi>Of Biſhops above Presbyters, there is but one belongs to a city. But here are many to one city, to</hi> Philippi, <hi>to</hi> Epheſus, <hi>and theſe were one and the ſame with Presbyters.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The denyall of the Propoſition he accounts contentious wrangling, whence this diſcourſe proceeds clear.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Argument from the ſame teſtimonies; <hi>The name of Biſhop is equally given to all the Elders,</hi> Phil. 1. <hi>All the miniſters ſalu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by that name, (for what reaſon can be imagined, ſuppoſing Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:64467:31"/>and Elders diſtinct, why he ſhould ſalute only the Biſhops and Deacons, and leave out all the other miniſters?)</hi> Acts 20. <hi>the ſame who are called Elders,</hi> v. 17. <hi>are Biſhops,</hi> v. 28. The ſame Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. with the ſeventh.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Argument, from the laſt teſtimonie; <hi>Where the names are uſed indifferently one for another, and the ſelfe ſame qualifications for office ſubjoyned to each name, there the ſelfe ſame office is ſet out under each name. But ſo it is here. The Apoſtle enjoyning</hi> Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus <hi>to appoint Elders, —if any be blameleſſe, &amp;c.</hi> v. 5, He gives the reaſon, <hi>v.</hi> 7. <hi>for a Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe, &amp;c.</hi> If Biſhop and Presbyter be not one and the ſame, the Apoſtle had not reaſoned at all; might it not be replyed? it is true, a Biſhop muſt be blameleſſe, &amp;c. but every Presbyter is not a Biſhop;</p>
               <p>Here we may take notice of the miſerable ſhifts of the Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuits, and with them our Prelates. <hi>The names,</hi> ſay they, <hi>were then common, but the office diſtinct.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Becauſe the names were common, and that perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually, therefore the father here, according to all reaſon in the world, argues the office one and the ſame. 2. Not only the names are common, but the qualifications for office, are here one and the ſame under thoſe names. The ſelfe ſame office is ſet forth; their gloſſe here doth yet further betray the nakednes of their evaſion. <hi>A Presbyter</hi> ſay they <hi>is comprehened in a Biſhop, for every Biſhop is a Presbyter,</hi> (though withal he bemore,) <hi>as every Captaine is a Souldier, and therefore the names are common.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Where Perſons different in peculiar Calling or Commiſſion, do yet agree in one common denomination, it cannot be ſaid they are one and the ſame; No man faith, (though every Captaine be a Souldier,) that a Captaine and a Souldier are one and the ſame; but here <hi>Jerome</hi> expreſſeth ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scripture, <hi>that Biſhop and Presbyter are one and the ſame.</hi> 2. In ſuch a difference of Perſons, the leſſe may be affirmed indefinitely, or univerſally of the greater; but not the greater of the leſſe; it is true, every Captain is a Souldier; but it is not true that every Souldier is a Captaine; but here the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop is affirmed of the Elder, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17. with 28. and <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. with <hi>v.</hi> 7. Their ſecond ſhift is as miſerable, (for this hold is ſo weak they are forced to quit it,) <hi>That in the Apoſtles times the office of Biſhop and Presbyter was diſtinct, but both at
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:64467:31"/>one time conferred upon the ſame Perſons.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This is to be wiſe above what is written, no ſuch thing any where hinted. 2. The higheſt operations are aſcribed to the Elders as ſuch to feed, to labour in the word and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, therefore the Biſhops office could not be above theirs. 3. How miſerably then had <hi>Jerome</hi> argued? <hi>What folly is this</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that any man ſhould preferre Deacons before Presbyters,</hi> (ſpeaking of the Presbyters of his time, when the cuſtome of the Church had obtained that Biſhops were above Presbyters,) <hi>that is before Biſhops; and thence carries on his diſpute, that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to divine inſtitution there is no difference.</hi> Now if this Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuitical Allegation was true, the Anſwer was ready; they had in the Apoſtles time the office of Presbyter and Biſhop both, though diſtinct, yet in one Perſon, as now they are diſtinct in ſeveral Perſons; therefore Presbyters now are not by divine inſtitution equall to them; the truth is, it is one office, which was then in one Perſon undivided, is now divided, and ſo ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red into ſeverall Perſons.</p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>Argument.</hi> From 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>If that which is challenged peculiarly to Biſhops, belong to the Preſbyters as ſuch, then their office is not diſtinct;</hi> but ſo it is; <hi>that which is challenged, &amp;c.</hi> No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more peculiarly challenged then <hi>Ordination,</hi> yet is that here by <hi>Jerome</hi> pleaded for the Presbyters, in this very queſtion, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in he is pleading the equality of (or identity rather) of Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops and Presbyters. The ſame we may argue from <hi>Act.</hi> 13.1. &amp;c. The ſeparating of <hi>Barnabas</hi> and <hi>Saul</hi> to their Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtery among the Gentiles by impoſition of hands, cannot well be conceived belonging to any other then to thoſe to whom it belongs to ſet a part by like impoſition of hands, the ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Miniſters of the word; at leaſt not to any inferiour to thoſe; But <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were ſeparate to their Miniſtery, not by Biſhops above Presbyters, but by Prophets and Teachers who were Presbyters. <hi>Object.</hi> The greater cannot be Ordain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the leſſe; <hi>Paul</hi> Ordained <hi>Timothy. Anſw.</hi> This impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of hands is of like nature, with Ordination at the leaſt; the Presbyters concurred with <hi>Paul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. Argument, From 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5.1.2. The Greek word (ſaith he) <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>over-ſeeing</hi> or <hi>taking the over-ſight,</hi> is more ſignificant, whence the name of a Biſhop is drawn; The Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:64467:32"/>is thus. <hi>Whatſoever operations belong to the Biſhop by his Office, the ſame belong to the Presbyter by his; therefore they are not diſtinct Officers, but one and the ſame.</hi> The former part is proved thus; <hi>All that belongs to the Biſhops office, is comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>which ſignifies to performe the part of a Biſhop; from whence the very name of Biſhop is derived; but whatſoever is comprehended in the word</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>belongs to the Preſbyters by expreſſe teſtimony here; they muſt act the part of Biſhops, which were they not the ſame with Biſhops, would be to uſurpe.</hi> Therefore if not onely Ordination but Juriſdiction be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Biſhops, the ſame by as authentique Commiſſion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to Presbyters or Paſtors and Teachers of ſeverall Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gations. Hence as formerly for Ordination, ſo for Juriſdiction, we may obſerve that it is to be performed without Biſhops di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct from and above Presbyters, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. <hi>per totum,</hi> there were then no Biſhops in <hi>Corinth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Apoſtle there excommunicated, <hi>verſ.</hi> 3. <hi>I have judged already, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Some (as <hi>Beza</hi> for one) hold excommunication prevented by publique rebuke, and repentance thereupon, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.6. the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> rendred puniſhment, ſignifies rebuke. 2. The Apoſtles judgement was a judgement of doctrinall deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, appointing them what to do, in caſe publike rebuke or admonition ſhould not reclaime him; not of juridicall executi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. The Church was to be gathered in the name and with the power of Chriſt, <hi>to deliver, &amp;c.</hi> 3. Had not this Church the ſame power with thoſe Churches <hi>Rev.</hi> 2? But they were to proceed by the Apoſtles direction, blamed that they had ſuffered ſuch and ſuch as the <hi>Nicolatians, Jezabel, &amp;c.</hi> The Apoſtle him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe not formally executing, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. All Church rule is diſtributed among the Elders or Presbyters; therefore to the Elders, as the Elders it belongs; and Elders and Biſhops are one and the ſame.</p>
               <p>Adde here (what is obſerved) the word <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Biſhop is never mentioned in the New Teſtament as belonging to a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall Church officer, but the actions therein required belong to any teaching Presbyter, are not thoſe peculiar actions challenged to the Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Argument</hi> from this laſt teſtimony, and 2 <hi>John</hi> 1 <hi>&amp;</hi>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:64467:32"/>3 <hi>John</hi> 1. <hi>There is no perpetual office in the Church above that which the Apoſtles hold in common with the perpetual officers, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring in the word and doctrine,</hi> and according to which they ſtile themſelves; but that is the office of Presbyters, as is cleare in theſe teſtimonies.</p>
               <p>All theſe Arguments we have here in <hi>Ierome's</hi> diſcourſe, and thus by him made uſe of; let us adde the</p>
               <p n="8">8. Argument. <hi>The office of Paſtor or Teacher, is an office of the higheſt denomination after the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts have ceaſed.</hi> Epheſ. 4.11. 1. <hi>To feed and to teach are higher acts then to rule in way of Diſcipline;</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.17. 2. Theſe are the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters of the word, given of Chriſt to the Church in all a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges <hi>for perfecting the Saints, for the work of the Miniſtry, for edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying the body of Chriſt,</hi> verſe 12. But every Miniſter of the word is by his office a Paſtor or Teacher.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> But Biſhops above Presbyters may be Paſtors above Paſtors, and Teachers above Teachers.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Thoſe acts and the power for them whereby they challenge ſuperiority, cannot make them above, becauſe they are of inferiour nature to the acts of feeding and teaching belonging to every Miniſter of the word.</p>
               <p n="2">2. All officers of one denomination, whether above them or below them, are equall in power and office; the Apoſtles and Evangeliſts above them, equall among themſelves; the Deacons below them, equall among themſelves; and what hint is there that theſe middle officers ſhould among themſelves be divided into extremes?</p>
               <p>Thus from Scripture. <hi>Jerome</hi> now goes on to ſhew the equali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Biſhops and Presbyters, as to their office by divine inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, partly by preventing an objection, partly by a famous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the Church of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> the objection he prevents in theſe words; But that afterwards one was choſen, who ſhould be preferred before the reſt, it was done for the remedy of ſchiſme, leaſt every one drawing the Church of Chriſt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſhould break it in pieces. The Summe is this; in the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times there was no difference, the Scripture holds them forth equall; this difference was made afterwards, occaſioned by ſchiſme, for the healing whereof the Church thought it expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient to take this courſe; but no ground in Scripture for this ine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality;
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:64467:33"/>and this he expreſſeth yet more clearly in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary upon <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.5. comparing the fifth and ſeventh <hi>v.</hi> together, thus he ſpeaks. Let us diligently attend the Apoſtles words, ſaying that thou mayeſt appoint Presbyters in every city, as I had appointed thee, who ſhewing what kind of Presbyter ought to be ordained in his following diſcourſe, thus he inferrs, for it behoves a Biſhop to be blameleſſe, as the ſteward of God; a Presbyter then is the very ſame with a Biſhop, (ſaith he) and before that by the inſtinct of the devill diviſions were made in religion, and they ſaid among the People, I am of <hi>Paul,</hi> I am of <hi>Apollo,</hi> but I am of <hi>Cephas,</hi> the Churches were governed by the Common Councell of the Presbyters; (theſe Presbyters not joyned to the Biſhop, as one above them, as it is here plaine, but all the Presbyters equall among themſelves joyning in this Common-Counſell,) the Father goes on; but after that every one thought thoſe whom he baptized, his owne, not Chriſts; it was decreed in the whole world, that one choſen from among the Presbyters, ſhould be ſet above the reſt, to whom all the care of the Church ſhould belong, and the ſeeds of ſchiſme ſhould be taken away.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Here we ſee that this cuſtome came in long after the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles times generally.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Nay, the Apoſtle ordered it thus in his time; for it is ſaid here, when one ſaid, <hi>I am of Paul,</hi> another, <hi>I am of Apollo, &amp;c.</hi> Then was this courſe taken; but it was in the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth</hi> in the Apoſtles time, that ſo they ſaid.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> That forme of words <hi>Jerome</hi> here uſeth aptly to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe the manner of Schiſme, but doth not point at that time, as if the Apoſtle had then taken this courſe, as is manifeſt, 1. When he had proved the equality of Biſhops and Presbyters, from Epiſtles written after the Epiſtle to the Corinthians, he yet ſaith afterwards this courſe was taken. 2. He doth not ſay when the Corinthians ſaid thus, but when they ſaid thus among the people, it was decreed not in <hi>Corinth,</hi> but in the whole world. 2. And as it was after the Apoſtles times, ſo that it had no ground in their writings, he goes on to ſhew by ſome of the ſame Scriptures, formerly uſed in this Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> which Scriptures he further in this place inſiſts upon. Some man may think (ſaith he,) that this is not the ſentence of the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:64467:33"/>but my owne, that a Biſhop and a Presbyter are one, and that one is the name of age, the other of office or duty; let him read the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. <hi>Philippi</hi> is of <hi>Mace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donia,</hi> and certainly in one city there could not be many Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, as they are called, but becauſe they called the ſame Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops at that time, whom they called alſo Presbyters, therefore the Apoſtle ſpake indifferently of Biſhops, as of Presbyters. Yet this may ſeeme doubtfull to ſome men, except it be confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by another teſtimony, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.17, 28. Mark this dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, (ſaith he,) how he calling the Presbyters of one city of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> afterwards cals the ſame Biſhops. If any man will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that Epiſtle which is written to the Hebrews in <hi>Pauls</hi> name, there alſo the care of the Church is equally divided among ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, foraſmuch as he writes to the people. <hi>Obey them that rule over you, &amp;c.</hi> Heb. 13.17. and <hi>Peter</hi> who from the firme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his faith received his name,—in his Epiſtle ſpeaks, ſaying, <hi>the Elders that are among you, I who am likewiſe your fellow El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, &amp;c.</hi> 1 <hi>Pe.</hi> 5.1.2. Theſe things I have therefore ſpoken, that we might ſhew, that amongſt the Ancient, Biſhops and Presbyters were the ſame, but by little and little, that the miſeries of diſſention may be plucked up, all the care was laid upon one. Therefore as the Presbyters know that they are by the cuſtome of the Church ſubject to him that is ſet over them: ſo let the Biſhops know, that they rather by cuſtome then the truth of the Lords order are greater then Presbyters, and that they ought to governe the Church in Commune; imitating <hi>Moſes,</hi> who when he had it in his Power alone to rule the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> choſe ſeventy, with whom he would judge the People. Hitherto <hi>Jerome</hi> upon <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.1. whoſe diſcourſe is ſo plain and cleare, that the very reading it over, anſwers all cavils ſtarted to obſcure his doctrine, touching the equality of Biſhops and Presbyters by divine inſtitution; and whereas in the cloſe of all he ſeems to parallel the Biſhop and his Presbyters with <hi>Moſes</hi> and his ſeventy Judges, that this in parallel is according to the cuſtome of the Church, not according to ſcripture rule, is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent by the words immediatly foregoing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:64467:34"/>
               <head>CHAP. IX.</head>
               <p>WE returne now to his Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius,</hi> and come to the inſtance of the Church at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> further con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming the equality of Presbyters and Biſhops, when he had ſaid (as formerly we quoted) in prevention of an objection; but that afterwards one was choſen, who ſhould be ſet before the reſt, it was done for the remedy of ſchiſme, leaſt every one drawing the Church of Chriſt to himſelfe ſhould break it in pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; he addes, for at <hi>Alexandria</hi> alſo, from <hi>Mark</hi> the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt, untill the time of <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> Biſhops, the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters alwayes named one, the Biſhop, who was choſen out of themſelves, and placed in an higher degree, as if an Army ſhould make a Generall, or the Deacons ſhould from among themſelves chuſe one whom they knew induſtrious, and call him Arch-Deacon; For what doth a Biſhop, Ordination except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that a Presbyter may not do?</p>
               <p>The ſumme of theſe words is, as at <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Philippi,</hi> in the Apoſtles time the Biſhops and Presbyters were one and the ſame, ſo after their time, till about two hundred and ſixty years, more or leſſe after Chriſt, they remained equall in office at <hi>Alexandria,</hi> (what change ſoever was made ſooner in ſome other Churches, occaſioned by ſchiſmes amongſt them,) only for more orderly Proceeding, one of the Presbyters was choſen by the reſt, to be in degree above the reſt, but not in office or diſtinct Power, as having no peculiar Ordination, and this man they called the Biſhop; that this is the true meaning of the words, it appears upon diſtinct conſideration of them, (here we muſt remember that his Prevention of the Objection follows immediately his Scripture teſtimonie; and the inſtance of <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> immediately follows that Prevention.)</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Conjunction <hi>alſo,</hi> or <hi>and,</hi> joyns this example of <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexandria,</hi> to the former of <hi>Epheſus</hi> and <hi>Philippi,</hi> (For at <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andria</hi> alſo.)</p>
               <p n="2">2. He makes a difference betwixt <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and thoſe before them, from <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt, whom they called Biſhops.</p>
               <p n="3">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:64467:34"/>
3. He ſhews what the difference was, that whereas <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius</hi> were by peculiar Ordination made Biſhops, as in office and Power above Presbyters, (as the like cuſtome had obtained earlier in other Churches, as appears in <hi>Cyprians</hi> E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles,) they that were before, were only choſen by the Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters, placed in an higher degree, and called Biſhops, but had no peculiar Ordination, (and therefore no peculiar office.) That they had no peculiar Ordination, is manifeſt. 1. By the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons by whom they were ſet in an higher degree, they were only the other Presbyters. But 1. Presbyters alone ſay the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates of Epiſcopacy, may not ordaine a Presbyter, much leſſe a Biſhop. 2. If they might ordaine a Biſhop, much more might they ordaine a Presbyter, and then what place for the office of a Biſhop in the Church above the Presbyter? Ordination be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one maine peculiar challenged to the Biſhop. Had it then been peculiar Ordination that had advanced theſe above the reſt, and ſo inveſted them with a peculiar office, it muſt have been Biſhops, not Presbyters, by whoſe hands they were lifted up. 2. By the explication ſubjoyned in two compariſons. 1. As if an Army ſhould make a Generall. Here the Army chuſing the Generall, anſwers to the Presbyters chuſing the Biſhop ſo called; As <hi>Jerome</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>He that is Generall only upon thoſe termes, hath no peculiar Commiſſion, it belongs to the Prince or State to give that;</hi> neither had he that was Biſhop any peculiar Ordination, according to the mind of this compariſon, which the next compariſon holds forth more clearly; ſuppoſe the Deacons ſhould agree among themſelves to chuſe out one whom they would call Arch-Deacon, here neither is, nor could be any peculiar Office or Ordination conferred upon this Arch-Deacon. Hence <hi>Jerome</hi> concludes, <hi>having no diſtinct Ordination, they had no diſtinct Power or Office;</hi> and that is the true mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe words; for what doth a Biſhop, Ordination ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted, that a Presbyter may not do? This is uſually otherwiſe interpreted. <hi>viz.</hi> that a Presbyter may do all that a Biſhop may do, only the act of Ordination excepted, he may not ordain. And 1. they that are for the divine right of Epiſcopacy will have the exception to be by divine inſtitution; but this is cleare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to interpret this clauſe contrary to <hi>Ieroms</hi> whole diſcourſe, both the Scope and Arguments of it. 2, Pleading the equality
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:64467:35"/>of Biſhops and Presbyters, or their identity rather, inſtanced in Impoſition of hands by the Presbytery. 3. This interpretation overthrows his diſcourſe in this very inſtance of the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> whence it is inferred, as we have ſeen by the naturall explication of this diſcourſe. But 2. they that are againſt E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, underſtand <hi>Ierome</hi> to ſpeak of the Practice of the Church in his time; as if he ſhould ſay there was no difference formerly; now there is only this, and that not by divine inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, but by the cuſtome of the Church. A Biſhop ordains, which a Presbyter may not do. This interpretation may ſtand with his former diſcourſe and with the truth; and this paſſing, there is nothing for Epiſcopacy by divine right; therefore to grant this, looſeth nothing of the cauſe in hand, but the truly naturall interpretation following upon the former diſcourſe, which hath concluded what is here inferred, ſeems to be that formerly given, Ordinarion excepted, ſignifying without Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation conferred, Ordination here paſſively not actively taken. Summe up the diſcourſe in this inſtance of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> Every diſtinct Church officer hath a diſtinct Ordination; but theſe Biſhops, ſo called in the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> till <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> had no diſtinct Ordination from that of Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byters: therefore they were no diſtinct Church-officers from them.</p>
               <p>Hence we have light diſcovering the truth againſt the three Pretences from antiquity, pleading the divine right of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy.</p>
               <p n="1">1. It is alledged, that ſuch and ſuch Apoſtles and Evangeliſts were ordained Biſhops of ſuch and ſuch Churches; among the reſt, <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt Biſhop of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> that they ordained their Succeſſors, and ſo Epiſcopacy hath run downe in a conſtant courſe from the Apoſtles times.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. This ſtory overthrows it ſelfe, as is obſerved by the learned. 1. What place is there for ordaining Apoſtles and Evangeliſts, Biſhops over ſuch and ſuch Churches, who as A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Evangeliſts, had already in every Church, what pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſoever a Biſhop can claime in any Church to which he is or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained? 2. Ordination is from the leſſe to the greater; if an Apoſtle or Evangeliſt firſt, be afterwards ordained a Biſhop, then is the office of an Apoſtle or Evangeliſt inferiour to that of a Biſhop.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:64467:35"/>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 2. That there was no ſuch Succeſſion of Biſhops, or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daining Biſhops diſtinct from and above Presbyters, is manifeſt in this inſtance of the Church of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> where till <hi>Hera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> a Biſhop was no other but one of the Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, by the choice and conſent of the reſt, ſet in an higher degree.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Another pretence from antiquity, is the Catalogues of Biſhops, ſucceeding each other in ſuch and ſuch Churches.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> How doth it appeare that theſe Biſhops had peculiar Ordination and above Presbyters? there is as formall a Cata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue given in of the Biſhops of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> as of any other Church ſucceeding <hi>Mark</hi> the <hi>Evangeliſt</hi> in this order; 1. <hi>Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anus.</hi> 2. <hi>Abilius.</hi> 3. <hi>Cerdo.</hi> 4. <hi>Primus.</hi> 5. <hi>Juſtus.</hi> 6. <hi>Eumenes.</hi> 7. <hi>Marcus.</hi> 8. <hi>Celadion.</hi> 9. <hi>Agrippas</hi> or <hi>Agrippinus.</hi> 10. <hi>Julia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus.</hi> 11. <hi>Demetrius.</hi> 12. <hi>Heraclas.</hi> 13. <hi>Dionyſius.</hi> Whereas yet we have it cleare from <hi>Ierome,</hi> that <hi>Heraclas</hi> was the firſt who had diſtinct Ordination and Office above a Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Pretence from antiquity, ſuch teſtimonies as are given to the honour and power of Biſhops by the Ancients; and here above all <hi>Ignatius</hi> helps at every turne.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Foraſmuch as five of his Epiſtles are granted by diverſe advocates of Epiſcopacy to be ſuch as do evidently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tray no little forgery, who ſhall aſſure us, that thoſe ſeven by them avouched in all things genuine, are ſo indeed? what more unlikely, then that they ſhould eſcape tampering by the ſame hands?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe ſeven moſt ſtood upon, are by very learned men (amongſt others <hi>Salmaſius,</hi>) judged in the very teſtimonies ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſpurious, and that not from blaſſe, but upon good grounds. 1. The arrogance of ſome of them; take that for one, in his Epiſtle to the Trallians, <hi>What is the Biſhop, but he that is ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly poſſeſt of all Principality and Authority, beyond all, as much as is poſſible for men to be poſſeſt? being made an imitatour, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Power of Chriſt who is God.</hi> He that can find here an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall ſpirit breathing, ſurely hath little acquaintance with the Apoſtles writings, ſaith <hi>Salmaſius;</hi> and indeed how unlike to that of the Apoſtle is it? 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5. <hi>Who then is</hi> Paul, <hi>and
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:64467:36"/>who is</hi> Apollo, <hi>but miniſters by whom you beleeved? &amp;c.</hi> This was <hi>Pauls</hi> way to take up ſchiſme; how contrary to this <hi>Igna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tius</hi> here for the Prevention of it? 2 Of the falſeneſſe of ſome, that in the ſame Epiſtle; <hi>Reverence the Biſhop as Chriſt, as the bleſſed Apoſtles commanded you.</hi> Where is this command? That, in his Epiſtle to the Smyrnians, <hi>Let that be accounted a firme Euchariſt, which is by the Biſhop adminiſtred, or by him to whom he ſhall have committed it; it is not lawfull without the Biſhop either to baptize or to offer, &amp;c.</hi> Hath not the Holy Ghoſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted preaching, and baptiſme, and adminiſtration of the Supper, joyntly to every Presbyter? this ſounds ill in every care, except of Papiſt or Prelate; the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> had no true baptiſme for about two hundred and ſixty years, if this be true doctrine; as for the Reformed Churches, they are in the ſame caſe. 3. The idolatrous ſtrayne of ſome; take that in the ſame Epiſtle, <hi>In the Church is nothing greater then the Biſhop, conſecrate to God for the ſalvation of the whole world.</hi> 4. The impertinencie of ſome, take that in his Epiſtle to the Phila<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>delphians; <hi>Let the Princes obey the Emperour, the Souldiers the Princes, the Deacons the Presbyters, thoſe High-Prieſts, the Presbyters and the Deacons, and the reſt of the Clergy;</hi> and who are they I wonder, and what part of the Clergy is the Deacon? <hi>with all the People, and the Souldiers, and the Princes, and the Emperour, let them obey the Biſhop.</hi> Setting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide other flawes, what impertinencie is here to enjoyne the Princes and the Emperour to obey the Biſhop, when there were not at this time, nor many years after any Emperour or Princes Chriſtian? Theſe are ſome few gleanings more of the like ſtamp there to be found; that not without reaſon it is by the learned conjectured, that about the beginning or middle of the ſecond Century, was this forged Author ſurreptitiouſly brought into the Church, about which time this kinde of Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy ſoaring above Presbytery began.</p>
               <p n="3">3. How little our prelates and their party regard his writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, (only they plead them to ſerve their own turne) is ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt, that we hear ſo little from them of ſubjection to the Presbyters and Deacons, which <hi>Ignatius</hi> urgeth ſo much in his Epiſtle to the Trallians, It is neceſſary that ye do nothing without the Biſhop, but that ye be in ſubjection likewiſe to the
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:64467:36"/>Presbytery, as to the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt. And ye ought by all means to pleaſe the Deacons, being — of the myſteries of Jeſus Chriſt.— The Presbyters are the great Councell of God, and the Chain of the Apoſtles of Jeſus Chriſt. In his Epiſtle to thoſe in Tarſus, Let the Presbyter be ſubject to the Biſhop; the Deacons to the Presbyters; the People to the Presbyters and the Deacons; they that keep this good order, my ſoul for theirs. Much more to the ſame purpoſe up and down in him; where <hi>Salmaſius</hi> conjectures this ſpurious Author was about the midſt, or towards the beginning of the ſecond century, whilſt the Presbytery yet retaind much of its authority.</p>
               <p>Now what do our Prelates and their party here? For Presbyters, they allow them no rule by way of jurisdiction; for Deacons, they have firſt changed their office, and then order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it ſo as it is never long ſtanding, being only a degree to Presbytery.</p>
               <p>And indeed here this <hi>Ignatius</hi> ſeemes to aſcribe that office and power to Deacons which the ſcripture takes no notice of, which hath appointed them to the ſervice of tables, not to preach and rule in the Church (as <hi>Jerome</hi> argues;) and this furthers diſcovers that this is no true <hi>Ignatius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. Conclude from <hi>Jerome,</hi> that before ſchiſme fell out in the Churches, and that long after the Apoſtles times, the Church was governed only by Presbyters; that the Biſhop above the Presbyters was brought into ſome Churches ſooner, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to others later; according as ſchiſme gave the occaſion; that it was about 260 years, ere this change was made in the Church of <hi>Alexandria;</hi> that whereſoever it was made, it ſtands not up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on divine authority, but upon Church Cuſtome, and this by Scripture ſtrongly proved; therefore theſe teſtimonies of <hi>Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natius,</hi> or whatſoever the like, ſo farre as they plead for Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy above Presbytery, cannot ſtand either with the truth of the Scripture, or the practice of the firſt and pureſt Churches.</p>
               <p>We returne to <hi>Jerome</hi> his Epiſtle to <hi>Evagrius;</hi> That which next follows concernes not the matter in hand, but is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the ſuperiority of the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> and againſt a perverſe cuſtome in <hi>Rome,</hi> that a Presbyter was ordained upon the teſtimony of a Deacon; that which concernes the preſent
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:64467:37"/>queſtion followes in theſe words, <hi>Preſbyter and Biſhop, one is the name of age, the other of dignity;</hi> whence to <hi>Titus</hi> and <hi>Timothy</hi> the Apoſtle ſpeaks of the Ordination of the Biſhop and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con concerning the Presbyters he is altogether ſilent, becauſe in the Biſhop the Presbyter alſo is contained; He that is ordained from the leſſe to the greater he is advanced; Therefore either let the Deacon be ordained from the Presbyter, (that is, let him that is firſt a Presbyter be afterwards ordained a Deacon) that the Presbyter may be proved leſſe then the Deacon into whom he encreaſeth from a little one; or if the Presbyter be or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained from the Deacon, let him know that he is leſſe in gaines, greater in miniſtery. And that we may know that the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call traditions were taken out of the Old Teſtament, what <hi>Aaron</hi> and his ſonnes, and the <hi>Levites</hi> were in the Temple, that let the Biſhops, and Presbyters, and Deacons challenge in the Church.</p>
               <p>Here we have two things confirming the equality of Biſhops and Presbyters; in the third place an objection is to be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, ſeeming to favour their inequality.</p>
               <p>The firſt thing confirming their equality, That Presbyter and Biſhop are different names of one and the ſame perſon, in one and the ſame office, as having one and the ſame ordination; and where it is ſaid the Presbyter is contained in the Biſhop, the meaning is not as the leſſe in the greater, but as one with him; thus he expreſt himſelfe in the beginning of this Epiſtle; this he hath ſtrongly pleaded all the way; thus againe in his Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tary upon 1 <hi>Titus,</hi> as was formerly quoted in theſe words. Some man may think that this is not the ſentence of the Scripture, but mine owne, that a Biſhop and Presbyter are one, and that one is the name of age, the other of office; let him read the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 1.1. &amp;c.</p>
               <p>The ſecond confirmation of their equality, that Ordination is from the leſſe to the greater; and therefore if the Deacon be greater then the Presbyter, he muſt from a Presbyter as a little one, grow by Ordination into a Deacon as a great one; this rule deſtroyes the foundation of Hierarchy; that the Apoſtles were towards the end of their dayes, (and ſo the Evangeliſts) or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Biſhops of certaine Cities, every one having his proper See; then from an Apoſtle or Evangeliſt as the leſſe, did he by
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:64467:37"/>Ordination, increaſe into a Biſhop as the greater; but this is too abſurd that a Biſhop ſhould be greater then an Evangeliſt, nay then an Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>The Objection to be removed follows in the laſt words; And that we may know that the Apoſtolicall traditions, &amp;c. where he cals the ſuperiority of Biſhops over Presbyters, then obtaining in the Church, an Apoſtolicall tradition.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. There was great difference betwixt the Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacy that then was, and the Prelacy as we have had it; as no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was done without the Biſhop, ſo nor without the reſt of the Miniſters and People.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His ſcope was to prove, and clearly he hath proved, that according to the Scriptures in the writings of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, there is no inequality at all betwixt Biſhop and Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byter, but they are one and the ſame.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The riſe of their inequality he makes the cuſtome of the Church, contra-diſtinguiſhed to the truth of the Lords order.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Therefore that he cals it an Apoſtolicall tradition, it can amount only to this; that what the Church did here, when by ſchiſmes occaſioned thereto, he conceives not contrary to A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtolicall Precept, in generall, (though particularly the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quality or identity rather of the Biſhop and Presbyter be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly held forth in their writings,) but rather that the Churches Practice here fell under ſome generall rule, as <hi>let all things be done to edifying,</hi> or the like.</p>
               <p>And here was the difference, as is obſerved by the learned, betwixt <hi>Jerome</hi> and <hi>Aerius;</hi> they both agreed, that accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to divine inſtitution, there was no inequality. <hi>Aerius</hi> would have this inviolably obſerved in the Church. <hi>Jerome</hi> thought the Church had liberty to make a difference, and that it was a great expedient againſt ſchiſme. Of the ſame mind with <hi>Ierome</hi> for equality by divine inſtitution, it is pleaded by ſome choicely learned amongſt our Writers of ſacred Controverſies, (<hi>Ames</hi> and <hi>Salmaſius</hi>) confeſt by a learned Authour among the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts, <hi>(Medina,)</hi> that <hi>Ambroſe, Auſtin, Sedulius, Primaſius, Chryſoſtome, Theodoret, Oecumenius</hi> and <hi>Theophylact</hi> were.</p>
               <p>This inſtruction then ſtands good, Biſhops in office above Presbyters, are no Church-Officers of divine inſtitution; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:64467:38"/>as it is pleaded by <hi>Jerome.</hi> I ſhall conclude this inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, with one queſtion?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> May the Church in any caſe, ſet up as an expedient an office in the Church, which is not of divine inſtitution.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> No, in no wiſe. It was appointed that the man of fin ſhould aſcend into his chayre; thence the Church diſcerned not the iniquity of thoſe beautifull ſteps, by which he was to aſcend; what the Church took for an expedient to prevent ſchiſme, proved an expedient to promote tyranny. His time of falling hath been comming on, in this laſt age, is more and more haſtening; hence this truth making not a little for it, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth clear and current in the Reformed Churches, that in the Church no office-Power is to be owned, but what is of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution. An Argument or two to confirme it.</p>
               <p n="1">1. As among Jewes, no order of Prieſts or Levites, but what was expreſſely appointed of God, was to be received; ſo in the Goſpel-Churches, no other order of Miniſteries. All by <hi>Moſes</hi> there, as a faithfull ſervant; All by Chriſt here, as a faithfull Sonne.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Chriſt is the onely Law-giver of his Church, the appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of office is a maine exerciſe of the Law-givers power, as in the kingdomes of men, ſo in the Kingdome of the Mediator.</p>
               <p n="3">3. All proper and eſſentiall meanes of worſhip muſt be of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine inſtitution. 1. Becauſe worſhip by other meanes is will-worſhip, and will-worſhip is hatefull unto God; 2. Becauſe it is God alone who can ſanctifie and bleſſe the meanes of worſhip; man can put no inſtrumentall efficacy unto meanes, therefore cannot he ordaine them; But office, or miniſtery in the Church, is a proper and eſſentiall meanes of worſhip; therefore it muſt be of no other then divine inſtitution. As for that worne Octje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus. Anſw.</hi> They were Evangeliſts, who as the Apoſtles, are ſucceeded by Paſtors and Teachers; above whom there is no Biſhop.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> The Angel of the Church 2 and 3. of the Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the Biſhop of each Church, a Paſtor of peerleſſe power in the Church.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Suppoſe by the Angel is meant a ſingular perſon, and he an eminent Paſtor, how doth it appear that he had di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinct power of Ordination and juriſdiction above the reſt? Why
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:64467:38"/>might it not be in thoſe Churches as in the Church of <hi>Alexandria</hi> from <hi>Mark</hi> the Evangeliſt, till <hi>Heraclas</hi> and <hi>Dionyſius,</hi> one in degree and order, not in office and diſtinct power above the reſt, to whom the Epiſtle is inſcribed?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Angel in the ſingular number, doth not of neceſſity infer a ſingular perſon; it is uſed in Scripture collectively diverſe times, as <hi>Pſal</hi> 34.7. <hi>The Angel of the Lord pitcheth his tents, &amp;c.</hi> that is the Angels of the Lord pitch their tents round about, &amp;c. ſo the Revelation frequently; the ſeven Angels that ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the ſeven trumpets, and the ſeven Angels that powred out the ſeven vials, were not ſeven ſingular Perſons, but ſeven Compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies or ſorts of men performing that ſervice.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Angel of the Churches, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. and 3. muſt be taken collectively, or the whole company of the miniſters of the Church, as is evident, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2.24. To you in the plurall number, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> writing to the Angel, as diſtinguiſhed from the reſt of the Church.</p>
               <p>Having ſeen the unwarrantableneſſe of the Dioceſan Biſhop, we ſhall not need to ſpeak of the true officers for rule in the Church; for Paſtors and Teachers, they are doubted by none, but the Epiſcopall Party; for ruling Elders to them adjoyned, as it hath been the doctrine and practice of the Reformed Churches generally; ſo of late there are diverſe diſcourſes, eaſie to be met with, fairly and clearly pleading their divine right; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the reſt, the way of the Church of Chriſt in <hi>New Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> the <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> &amp;c. the ſumme of the ſurvey of diſcipline, by Maſter <hi>Hooker.</hi> I ſhall therefore paſſe to another inſtruction, about particular Congregations.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:64467:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>CHAP. X. The ſeventh Inſtruction.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>To a particular Congregation of viſible Saints, furniſhed with of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, it belongs to exerciſe all parts of diſcipline with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in it ſelfe. In it power of all diſcipline, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all power of diſcipline, or not.</p>
               </argument>
               <p n="1">1. The Churches inſtanced in Scripture, of <hi>Corinth, Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus, &amp;c.</hi> thus far they ſeem to have been each a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Congregation.</p>
               <p n="1">1. All the ordinary officers were choſen by the People, as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers in command to the flock in common; this appears from the doctrine of the Peoples choyce formerly; of the Church of <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinth,</hi> their miniſters were choſen, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> it ſeeming good to the whole Church, in the time of <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mens Romanus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. In the exerciſe of diſcipline, the People generally concur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the officers jointly; this from the doctrine of diſcipline formerly; thoſe officers formerly by them in common choſen; and thus the Churches true liberty was preſerved.</p>
               <p>As for that Objection, the number of Chriſtians and officers were ſo great, they could not ordinarily meet in one place for worſhip; the anſwer is, ſuppoſe that to be truth; yet might the officers interchangeably adminiſter to them, as officers in common to the flock in common, as wel for all publick admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrations of worſhip, as for diſcipline joyntly.</p>
               <p>As for the other maine objection, variety of languages; therefore their Congregations, muſt be many and fixt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> There were interpreters of languages, that thoſe who in the Congregation underſtood not their language ſpoken in, might by interpretation underſtand it; this argues their Congregations were not fixt, according to the difference of languages.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Where there are all ſorts of power for diſcipline, there is an entire right for the exerciſe of it; for power is for exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:64467:39" rendition="simple:additions"/>but in every Congregation there are all ſorts of Power; there is power of order, and power of office; and for of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice-power, there are both ſorts of officers, Elders labouring in the word and doctrine, and others for rule with them; and in this they of the Presbyterian and Congregationall way agree.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Where our Saviours rule may be obſerved, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.15, 16, 17. there is entire power of diſcipline; But in every Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion ſo framed, that rule may be obſerved. Admonition, firſt ſingle, then before a witneſſe or two, and laſtly by the Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Where authoritative ſuſpenſion may be, there may be excommunication; but in every ſuch Congregation authorita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive ſuſpenſion may be; this later is granted, the former is thus confirmed. Where there is power of Church-admonition, there is power of excommunication; <hi>Mat.</hi> 18.17. but where there is power of authoritative ſuſpenſion, there is power of Church-admonition. 1. Suſpenſion ſuppoſeth ſuch admonition. 2. Admonition is a leſſe act of power and juriſdiction then Suſpenſion is.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Where there is right to entire Church-fellowſhip, in the Ordinances of Publicke Worſhip, and private Communion, there is right for the exerciſe of diſcipline; this appears thus; A ſcandalous ſinner in ſuch a ſociety retained, is leaven, leavening the whole lump, involving the whole ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety in guilt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. therefore it is their duty, and in their power to caſt him out. But in every Congregation ſo framed, there is right for entire Church-fellowſhip, &amp;c. This is not que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtioned.</p>
               <p>Hence to the Church of <hi>Corinth</hi> power is aſcribed, and ſhe blamed for not caſting out the inceſtuous Perſon, not becauſe ſhe had thus and thus many officers, but becauſe ſhe was a Church entirely framed for diſcipline, having in her all kinde of power for that purpoſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:64467:40"/>
               <head>CHAP. XI. The eighth Inſtruction. <hi>To a Congregation of viſible Saints, not yet poſſeſt of officers, it belongs to poſſeſſe themſelves of them.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HEre are two things fall into conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.
<list>
                     <item>Election.</item>
                     <item>Ordination.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. For election, foraſmuch as it is the Peoples right, as ſuch, as hath been proved in the third inſtruction, hence it belongs to any number of them joyned together into a congregation, by choyce to call Officers to themſelves.</p>
               <p n="2">2. If they have not this right among themſelves, whence ſhall it be derived to them? 1. From other Churches; but how came they by their officers? 2. From a Synod; but a Synod is made up of the delegates of ſetled Congregations, therefore Congregations muſt firſt be ſetled. There is the ſame anſwer for a Claſſis. 3. From the civill magiſtrate. This hath been prevented in the fifth Inſtruction. 4. From the combination of diverſe miniſters. Be it granted that the People now about to forme into a diſciplinary Congregation, and to chuſe their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ought to conſult and follow the juſt guidance of able and faithfull Miniſters proceeding aright, in directing them; yet ought not thoſe miniſters to appoint officers over them, whom they ſhall not upon their directions freely conſent to; Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to them, not Paſtors and Rulers over them, may they with the help of civill authority fix among them. In a ſetled Congregation, where by death, or removall, or cenſure, only one officer is wanting, the reſt of the officers have not Power to impoſe another upon the Congregation, without her choyce, as is cleare by the third Inſtruction, formerly ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the right of the Peoples Election; but thoſe her owne of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers have greater authority over her, then any combination of Miniſters not yet diſciplinarily ſetled in ſeverall Congregations. Much leſſe hath any one Miniſter this power.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For Ordination. Not to diſpute whether it be the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:64467:40"/>Conſtitution of an officer, or the ſolemne approbation of him, by the Peoples Election formally conſtitute;</p>
               <p n="1">1. According to Scripture-rule, and thence the Practice both of the Primitive and Reformed Churches, it ought to ſucceed the Peoples Election; this is cleare for a Paſtor or Teacher to a Church gathered, whatſoever may be ſaid for a Teacher by office for gathering a Church.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Be it granted that the People having choſen their offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, ought to preſent them, (having the opportunity,) to ſome approved Miniſters for Impoſition of hands; it muſt likewiſe be granted, that thoſe Miniſters without juſt exception againſt that People or their choyce, ought not to refuſe the officer ſo preſented.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Suppoſing ſuch Ordination cannot be had, whether are the People to remaine without the publike miniſtery, and ſo without the publike Ordinances of worſhip and diſcipline; or doth their election and approbation alone in this exigency, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſt with office-power? Let us indeavour to frame a judgement by inſtance of a caſe or two.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Suppoſe a company of Saints caſt upon a remote Iſland, not neare any Churches or Miniſters, and there they are to fixe their habitations; may they not, (having Perſons among them fitted,) ſettle among themſelves a publike miniſtery?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Suppoſe a company of People in the midſt of the Romane territories, ſavingly enlightned with the truth of the Goſpel; 1. Ought they not, having fit Perſons among them, to chooſe out ſome for the publick miniſteries of the Church? 2. Ought they in caſe Impoſition of hands might be ſo obtained, to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent them to the Romane Prelates for it? <hi>Beza</hi> ſaith no. 3. In caſe that they either ought not, or it could not be obtained, might they not without it, ſettle their officers among themſelves?</p>
               <p n="3">3. In caſe then that a Congregation ſtands convinced of the true bounds of the matter of the viſible Church and the true confine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of diſcipline to them within thoſe bounds, &amp; hath fit Perſons for the publike miniſtry among them, but can not obtain Impoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of hands upon their choyce from Miniſters ſought unto, as differing in judgement about the matter and diſcipline of the Church, why hath not this Congregation the ſame liberty in this caſe, that the others had in the former?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="74" facs="tcp:64467:41"/>
                  <hi>Object.</hi> Here they make themſelves Judges.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. So in the former inſtances. 2. What way ſoever they are in, or what Governement ſoever they are under, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept they ſee it with their owne eyes to be according to rule, it is but blinde walking, and blind obedience, and therefore unac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> In caſe they go wrong, and the miniſtery with other Chriſtians againſt them be right, what is to be done?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For them, they are to obey their own conſciences; though we cannot ſay erring Perſons have a right to obey their owne conſciences, yet may we ſay that it is their duty. An erro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous conſcience bindes.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Miniſtry and Orthodox Chriſtians againſt them; as the Church is to proceed againſt Schiſmaticks, ſo are they againſt thoſe, in caſe they themſelves be in a State of diſcipline, and judge the offence of that moment.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> Suppoſe they be right, and the Miniſtry and Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans againſt them wrong.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. For the miniſtery, &amp;c. (as formerly on the other part,) here is their duty, though not their right, to proceed as the Church ought to do againſt Schiſmaticks.</p>
               <p n="2">2. For the Congregation, it is their duty and their right to proceed, as in other caſes the true Church is to hold on her way, though perſecuted as ſchiſmaticall and hereticall.</p>
               <div type="conclusion">
                  <head>CONSECTARY.</head>
                  <p>With more evidence yet; A Miniſter conſenting with diverſe Chriſtians, nay diverſe Miniſters ſo conſenting, may together with thoſe Chriſtians joyning with them, ſettle diſcipline among themſelves; In this caſe here is all intrinſecall power for ſetling diſcipline.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:64467:41"/>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
